国家宝藏2：夺宝秘笈
华盛顿  1865年4月14日
南北战争结束后第五天
他在里面
He's in the other room.
- 你是托马斯・盖茨？ - 对
- Are you Thomas Gates？ - Yes.
有些东西想让你看看
We got something that we'd like you to take a look at.
听说你很会解谜
I hear you're quite good with puzzles and riddles.
- 是条加密的信息 - 这是普莱费厄密码
- It's a coded message. - It's a Playfair cipher.
- 普莱费厄密码？ - 你能解码吗？
- Playfair cipher？ - Can you decode it？
解那种密码得要有密钥
Cipher's impossible to decode without the key.
- 密钥是什么意思？ - 一个关键字句
- What do you mean by "a key"？ - A keyword or phrase.
我相信你需要东西的就在这里
I believe what you need is right there.
凡人皆要还之债！
这得花点时间
It'll take some time.
走吧，我拿日记，待会再跟你会合
Go on. I'll take your diary. I'll meet up with you later.
只要算好距离，保准你能正中靶心(舞台上正表演《我们的美国表弟》)
…calculate the distance and you're sure to hit the mark
这样不仅打手枪很准，打炮也很准哦
in about most things as well as shootin'.
…我要将它浇你身，就像狗头浇上粪
…ready to pour out all over you like apple sass over roast pork.
我得当心点，不能把手上的东西 泼到可怜的德・布茨老爷身上
I'll take care not to give up my hold on poor De Boots
要泼也得等了解美国人之后再泼
till I am quite sure of the American.
嗯，我女儿真乖
Ah, that's my own girl.
奥古斯塔，亲爱的，去你房间怎么样
Augusta, dear, to your room.
展示一下你的内在美吧，我的好姑娘 特别是那片幽深的草场，令人心荡漾
…to turn you inside out, old gal, you sockdologizing old man-trap.
【拉丁语】打倒专制君主！
Sic semper tyrannis！
神殿…
Temples.
黄金…
Gold.
锡沃拉？这是张藏宝图！
Cibola？ This is a treasure map.
KGC？你是金环骑士会成员！叛国贼！
KGC？ You're Knights of the Golden Circle. You're a traitor.
你们都是叛国贼
You're all traitors.
- 林肯总统被刺了！ - 出去！全都出去！
- President Lincoln's been shot！ - Everybody, out！ All of you！
杀手仍然在逃
Killer's on the loose！
马上破译密文，本人感激不尽
I'd much appreciate it if you'd finish deciphering that code now.
- 爸爸！ - 战争结束了！
- Dad！ - The war is over.
不！
No！
- 不要 - 别
- No！ - No！
你错了
You're wrong about that.
战争才刚开始
The war has only just begun！
查尔斯，“凡人皆要还之债…”
Charles. The debt that all men… men pay.
凡人皆要还之…
The debt that all men p…
爸！不要死！
Dad！ No, please！
别死，这不公平
Come back. It's not fair.
救命！来人，救命啊！
Help！ Somebody help, please！
所以，我在此重述
So recapping:
金环骑士会是一个南方的极端团体
The Knights of the Golden Circle was a Southern extremist group,
他们在北方活动，暗中破坏联邦政府
operating in the north to subvert Union forces.
如果那几页著名的布斯日记没被托马斯烧毁
Had Thomas not burned the legendary missing pages from the Booth diary,
杀手可能早已找到大批黄金宝藏
the killers may have found a vast treasure of gold,
而联邦政府也可能输掉南北战争
and the Union may well have lost the Civil War.
谢谢大家
Thank you.
感谢本和帕特里克・盖茨两位…
I'd like to thank Ben and Patrick Gates.
谢谢
Thank you.
为我们讲述了一个精彩绝伦的传奇 以及托马斯・盖茨这位平民英雄
And say what a wonderful addition Thomas Gates is to our civilian heroes exhibit.
谢谢大家
Thank you.
谢谢，尼克尔斯博士，我只希望我爷爷
Thank you, Dr. Nichols. I only wish my grandfather
今天也能到场参与盛会
had been here to see this wonderful day.
抱歉，我有个问题想问
Excuse me. I have a question I'd like to ask.
你认为那页被焚毁的布斯日记上…
What do you think happened to that Booth diary page
- 究竟写了什么呢？ - 可能永远没法知道了
- that was pulled out of the fire？ - We may never know.
可能没办法
Perhaps.
也可能有办法
Perhaps not.
和你们一样，我的家族里也有位曾曾祖父
You see, I have one of those great-great-granddaddies, like you,
他名叫塞拉斯・威尔金森
way up in my family tree, name of Silas Wilkinson.
他曾说过一个林肯被刺当晚的故事
He used to tell a story about the night Lincoln was shot.
依他的说法
As Silas tells it,
布斯当晚并没有找托马斯・盖茨 谈什么藏宝图的事
Booth didn't seek out Thomas Gates regarding the treasure map that night.
是托马斯召集聚会
It was Thomas who called the meeting.
计划暗杀林肯
A meeting to plan the assassination of Lincoln.
- 太荒谬了 - 你说谎！
- How absurd. - That's a lie！
女士们先生们，请看…
Ladies and gentlemen, I present to you…
这张纸就是约翰・布斯日记中遗失的一页
…one of the missing pages from the infamous diary of John Wilkes Booth
上面有托马斯・盖茨的名字 和其他凶手的名字在一起
with the name Thomas Gates written on a list along with all the other killers.
- 这是拉丁文？ - 布斯曾学过拉丁文
- And Latin？ - Booth was a student of Latin.
他射杀林肯后大喊 “Sic semper tyrannis”
He shouted, "Sic semper tyrannis" after he shot Lincoln.
- 打倒… - 打倒专制君主，我们知道
- "Thus always to… " - "Thus always to tyrants. " We know.
- 萨拉特，copiae？ - copiae意思是军需供应
- "Surratt, copiae"？ - Military supplies.
玛丽・萨拉特被控有罪并处以绞刑
Mary Surratt was convicted and hanged
罪名是为布斯提供步枪和瞄准镜
for supplying Booth with a rifle and field glasses.
- 托马斯・盖茨，artifex - 意思是设计师
- "Thomas Gates, artifex. " - "Designer"
- 或者说策划者 - 我知道这字的意思
- or "mastermind. " - I know what it means.
一定是他策划暗杀的
He must have, uh, planned the assassination.
- 我明白了 - 也可能是策划别的事情
- I see. - Could mean mastermind of anything.
你看见没有？后面的内容被烧掉了
You see that？ Burned out right there.
我知道，对你而言这事情很难接受
I can only imagine how difficult this must be for you.
- 请问，这位先生… - 威尔金森
- May I, Mr？ - Wilkinson.
我来看看这页纸和布斯日记是否吻合
I'll see if this new page matches the Booth diary.
这简直是侮辱，你说我的祖父是个骗子
This is an outrage. You're calling my grandfather a liar.
你的意思是，我的曾曾祖父是个骗子
With respect, now you're calling my great-great-granddaddy a liar.
没错，我就是这个意思 我所说的不是从什么历史书里查来的垃圾
Yes, sir, I am. This isn't some garbage from a history book.
而是我祖父亲口告诉我的
My grandfather told me this story himself.
- 他的眼睛告诉我那些都是真话 - 我很遗憾，先生，真的很遗憾
- I saw the truth of it in his eyes. - I'm sorry, sir. I truly am.
这纸还得接受全面检测，然后才能做定论
We'll test this thoroughly, Patrick, to authenticate it.
怎么可能…
It can't be.
总统府的地图
Maps to presidents' houses.
有钥匙却没有要开的锁
Keys to locks that don't exist.
这是为什么呢？我究竟在找什么？
What's the point？ What am I looking for？
证据，证据，证据…
Proof, proof, proof.
什么证据呢？
What proof？
圣殿宝藏，作者 莱利・普尔
这本书是讲圣殿骑士宝藏的吗？
Oh, wow. Is this a book about the Templar treasure？
对，里面有讲到圣殿骑士的宝藏 但也有说到其它很多事
Yes, it is about the Templar treasure, but it's also about other things.
阴谋理论，民间传说… 及其它一些已被证实的神话
Conspiracy theories, urban legends and other myths that are true.
- 作者是不是在这儿签名售书啊？ - 作者就是在下
- So the author's here signing copies？ - I'm the author.
- 你就是？ - 嗯，你看
- You are？ - Yeah. See, uh…
那里面有我的照片
There's a picture of me right there.
我认为那张拍的相当不错
I think it's a pretty good picture.
我听说宝藏是那个 叫本杰明・盖茨的人发现的
I thought that guy, Benjamin Gates, found the treasure.
是本发现的没错，但我是他的搭档
Well, yes, Ben did, but I am the co-finder.
从没听说过
- Oh, I've never heard of you. - Oh！
我的天，你就是本・盖茨？
Oh, my gosh. Are you Ben Gates？
- 是的，我就是 - 你是不是有辆红色法拉利？
- Yes. Yes, I am. - Do you own a red Ferrari？
- 对，我有 - 嗯，它要被拖走了
- Yes, I do. - Well, it's being towed.
等等，那是我的车
Wait！ Wait！ That's my car！
你的法拉利呢？
Where's the Ferrari？
- 被国税局没收了 - 国税局？
- IRS impounded it. - The IRS？
说来滑稽，我的会计帮我
Funny story. My accountant set up a corporation
在一个虚构的岛上设立了一家公司
on an island that didn't exist
还告诉我富人们都是这么干的
and assured me that that's how rich people do it.
后来么，就有人来查我的账 还罚了一大笔钱，外加利息
Then I got audited and slapped with a huge fine plus interest.
知道五百万元要交多少税吗？
Wanna know what taxes are on five million dollars？
要交六百万元
Six million dollars.
我说完了
But enough about me.
你最近怎么样？
What's new with you？
女朋友把我赶出来了，我目前和我爸一起住
Well, my girlfriend kicked me out, I'm living with my dad,
- 还有我的祖辈刺杀了林肯总统 - 不错
- my family killed President Lincoln. - All right.
我要你帮忙
I need your help.
不敢相信你竟然连自己家都要用闯的
I can't believe you have to break into your own house.
我得拿到阿比盖尔的工作证 这样就能查阅布斯的日记了
I need to get Abigail's ID. She has access to the Booth diary page.
为什么不直接找阿比盖尔帮忙？
Why don't you ask Abigail for her help？
她把安防密码都改了，莱利 她现在连话都不想和我说
She changed the alarm code, Riley. She's not going to talk to me.
好吧
All right.
我们有30秒时间来解除警报
We have 30 seconds after the alert starts to disable the alarm.
开始
Go.
或许我不该问，但你和她究竟怎么了？
I'll probably regret asking this, but what happened with you and Abigail？
我不知道…她最近总是说“那么”这个词
I don't know. I don't know. She started using the word "so" a lot.
“那么”？
"So？"
比如说“那么我的意见无关紧要咯”
Yeah, like, "So, I guess my opinion doesn't matter. "
“那么说你总比我高明咯” “那么我是形同虚设的咯”
"So, you seem to always know what's best. " "So, I guess I'm invisible. "
我已经从这儿搬走了，正在协商怎么分家具
Now I've moved out, we're dividing furniture…
Oh.
不能和女人一起住 尤其不能和换了安防密码的女人一起住
Women. Can't live with them, especially if they change the alarm codes.
你25秒就搞定了
You did that in 25 seconds.
所以我总劝别人，还是养条狗好
That's why I tell people to get a dog.
- 找到了 - 好，我们走
- Got it. - All right, let's go.
那不是阿比盖尔的车
That's not Abigail's car.
她在和人约会
She was on a date.
那个男的，不就是白宫的那家伙么
Isn't that that guy？ The White House guy？
下周一是白宫复活节“滚彩蛋”大赛 如果你没什么…
The White House Easter Egg Roll is next Monday. Maybe if you're not…
这人挺怪的
He's weird！
如果孩子们没找到所有彩蛋怎么办？
What happens if kids don't find all the eggs？
你上班在博物馆，回家还住博物馆？
Wow. You work in a museum, and you live in one.
差不多吧
Pretty much.
伶牙俐齿啊，她一定喜欢上他了
What clever repartee. She must like him.
好吧，我带你参观一下这房子
All right, let me give you a tour of the house.
- 好的 - 实际上这里是…
- OK. - That's actually kind of…
阿比盖尔
Oh, Abigail.
- 你到这儿来干嘛？ - 我只是来拿点东西
- What are you doing here？ - I just needed to get some things.
- 康纳，很高兴又见到你了 - 你好盖茨
- Connor, good to see you again. - Gates.
你怎么进来的，本？
How did you get in, Ben？
莱利，给我出来
Riley！ Come out here！
什么事？
What？
嘿，你怎么来了？这里是你家，但是…
Hey！ What are you doing here？ I mean, it's your house, but…
我寄了本我写的书给你，看了吗？
I sent you a copy of my book. Did you get a chance？
不，我还没有读
- No, I haven't read it yet. - Mm.
我认识你，你是白宫的管理人
I know you. You're the White House curator.
- 我是莱利，我们以前见过面，就在… - 对，你是本的助手
- I'm Riley. We met, uh, back in… - Right. You're, uh, Ben's assistant.
什么？
What？
也许我该走了
Um, maybe I should go.
- 嗯，我真的很… - 明晚一起吃饭好吗？
- Yeah, I'm really… - Dinner tomorrow night？
我明天已经有安排了
I… I actually already have plans for tomorrow.
你有吗？
You do？
- 你当然早安排了 - 但我星期五有空
- Of course you do. - But I'm free on Friday.
那太好了
- Awkward. - Oh, great.
- 晚安 - 晚安
- Good night. - Good night.
真不敢相信，你竟然擅闯民宅
I cannot believe you broke in.
- 你拿了什么？ - 都是我自己的东西
- What did you take？ - It's just my things.
交出来，本
Hand it over, Ben.
我得去看布斯日记新发现的那页
I need to see the Booth diary page.
你早已经看过了，上面没有藏宝图
You saw the page yourself. There is no treasure map on it.
但那上面有发现藏宝图的密码 有人用光谱分析过那页纸吗？
No, it's a cipher leading to a map. Anyone spectral-image the page？
没必要，墨水书写的字迹清晰可见
No need to. The ink writing on the page is clearly visible.
可能有的字迹被抹去或者褪色了呢？
It could have been erased or faded.
你是文件保管部门的主管，你应该知道
You're the director of document conservation. You know this.
不归我管，那不是我的部门
Not up to me. It's not my department.
你管的就是那个部门的上级部门
That department reports to your department.
拜托，就用红外线看一次
Come on. One look under infrared.
波士顿茶几可以归你
You can have the Boston Tea Tables.
两张都归我？
Both of them？
这张纸我们已经看了几个小时了
We've been looking at this page for hours.
上面什么都没有
There's nothing there.
本，我认为在这张纸上什么也找不到
Ben, I really don't think we're going to find anything on this page.
你不妨这么想，等到一百年之后
In a hundred years, no one's going to remember
提起暗杀林肯的刺客 大家只会记得布斯一个人的名字
anyone involved in the Lincoln assassination besides Booth.
这可不一定 记得有句老话叫“他，玛德”么？
That's not true. Do you know the expression, "His name is mud"？
- 是的，当然记得 - 你记得？
- Yes. Of course. - You do？
- 那你知道这句话的出处吗？ - 除了你还有谁会知道
- You know the origin of the expression？ - Does anyone but you？
塞缪尔・玛德医生被控是刺杀林肯的同谋
Dr. Samuel Mudd was convicted of being a co-conspirator
后因证据不足，终被法庭释放
in the Lincoln assassination. The evidence was circumstantial.
但那已经无济于事了
He was later pardoned, but it didn't matter.
到现在玛德这名字都没翻身 我不能让盖茨这两个字蒙羞
Mudd's name still lives in infamy. And I will not let Thomas Gates' name be mud.
- 本 - 什么？
- Ben. - What？
看这里
Look at this.
看见没有？
- See that？ - Oh.
- 看着好像有字，不是吗？ - 是啊，那几个字好像是“看不清”
- That's quite something, isn't it？ - Yeah. It says "smudge. "
什么都不是啊
It's nothing.
是上一页墨水渗透的痕迹，翻过来看看
Residual ink from the facing page. Flip it.
字母是反的
The letters are backwards.
- 这是密码 - 没错
- It's a cipher. - Yes. It is.
一组密码，字母是成对的，看见没？
A cipher. See how the letters are coupled？
普莱费厄密码字母就是成对的 这可以证明他所说的不是谎言
Playfair ciphers encode letters in pairs. This could prove his story.
除非你能破译密码，但这不能证明什么
Unless you decode the cipher, this does not prove a theory.
那没问题，我们只要找到 由五个字母组成的关键字就行了
That's OK. We need a five-letter keyword.
- 那关键字是？ - 我还不知道
- What's the keyword？ - I don't know yet.
- 好吧 - 能打印出来给我吗？
- All right. - Uh, can I get a printout of this？
英语单词可是成千上万啊
There's a billion words in the English language.
还得符合逻辑…让我们从头开始吧
Got to be a logical… Let's start from the beginning.
从A开始…Aardvark（意为土豚）…
A. Aardvark.
我不是故意和你们唱反调 但是我认为已经来不及了
Don't want to rain on your parade here, but I don't think this is gonna stop
尼克尔斯博士明天就要 对外宣布有关该页的发现了
Dr. Nichols from announcing the discovery of the page tomorrow.
等一下，能不能请他等我证明了 托马斯的清白之后再宣布呢？
No, now, wait. Can't you ask him to wait until I prove Thomas is innocent？
那假如他不是清白的呢？
What if he isn't innocent？
联邦调查局总部 约翰・埃德加・胡佛大厦
长官，我们的老朋友本・盖茨又上新闻了
Sir？ Looks like our old friend Ben Gates is in the news again.
他又发现什么了？亚特兰蒂斯吗？
What did he find now？ Atlantis？
布斯日记的遗失页重现江湖
A guy came forward with a missing Booth diary page.
这还不是最精彩的，听听这个
That's not the best part. Listen to this.
在这张写有暗杀林肯的同谋者名单中
"On the page are the names of the conspirators
赫然列有一名之前不为人知的共谋者 托马斯・盖茨
in the Lincoln assassination, as well as a previously unknown conspirator,
托马斯・盖茨据说是寻宝猎人 本杰明・富兰克林・盖茨的曾曾祖父
Thomas Gates. Thomas Gates is said to be the great-great-grandfather of treasure hunter Benjamin Franklin Gates. "
- 我还以为就我的亲戚是坏蛋呢 - 这个威尔金森是什么来头？
- Thought my relatives were bad. - What do we know about this Wilkinson？
- 长官？ - 就是这个拿出这张纸的家伙
- Sir？ - Guy claims he had this page
都藏了140年，为什么今天才跳出来？
for 140 years then just suddenly comes forward with it？
- 为什么？ - 我们会查清楚的
- Why？ - We'll find out.
不错
Better.
Bacon（培根）
Bacon.
- 继续 - 这样太傻了
- Keep going. - That's stupid.
- 你老爹怎样了？ - 接着干你的
- How's he doing？ - Keep working.
我们非常感激威尔金森家族
We're grateful to the Wilkinson family
能将这张纸公诸于世
for coming forth with the page.
该页日记上列有之前不为人知的共谋者 托马斯・盖茨
On the page is a name of a previously unknown conspirator, Thomas Gates.
- 尼克尔斯也中邪了，看过这个没有？ - 爸爸，别看那个了
- Nichols has bought into it. See？ - Would you stop watching that.
都已经传上网了
It's on the Internet！
- 势不可挡了 - 盖茨可能就是策划者…
- No stopping it now. - Gates may have been the architect…
- 没有一点同情心 - 你知道真相，这就足够了
- They have no understanding. - You know the truth.That's all that matters.
你从查尔斯爷爷那里听到的故事才是真的
You heard the story from Grandpa.
故事？那家伙拿出的是证据 他就能证明一切
The story？ This guy's got evidence. He's got everything.
我们只有故事，什么都没法证明
We have a story. We have nothing.
盖茨家族扬眉吐气才没多久
For one brief moment, the Gates family could hold its head up.
- 现在又变成一群疯子了 - 但我们不是骗子
- Now we're a bunch of crazies. - But we're not liars.
威尔金森说是托马斯・盖茨一手策划了 美国历史上最黑暗的时刻
Wilkinson is saying that Thomas Gates was a mastermind to one of the darkest hours in U.S. History.
而且为了掩盖真相，他还焚烧了日记
And he burned the diary page to cover that up.
但你我都知道他之所以烧掉那页日记
You and I both know he burned the page
是为了阻止布斯和他的人找到宝藏
to keep Booth's men from finding the treasure.
那就是我们要去证明的东西
That's what we're going to prove.
- 只有一个方法能证明 - 得找到宝藏
- Only one way to prove it. - Find the treasure.
必须找到它，而且你得帮我一起找
You've got to find it. You're going to help me find it. So come on.
把查尔斯爷爷说过的故事再讲一遍
Let's hear the story again from Grandpa Charles.
爷爷听到他爸爸说到“藏宝图”
Grandpa heard his father say, "Treasure map. "
- 然后外面就乱起来了 - 那些都说过了，之后呢？
- Then there was a commotion. - Got all that. Anything after that？
他有说过什么，做过什么吗？随便什么
Anything he said, something he did？ Anything at all？
- 慢着… - 怎么了？
- Wait a minute. - What？
他握住他儿子的手
He took his son's hand.
看着儿子的眼睛，用最后一口气说到
He looked him in the eye, and he said, with his dying breath,
- 凡人皆要还之债 - 凡人皆要还之债？
- "The debt that all men pay. " - "The debt that all men pay"？
托马斯已经还了
The debt that Thomas paid.
是五个字母
That's five letters.
试试“Death”（死亡）
Try "Death. "
- 什么？ - 是密钥
- What？ - It's the keycode.
凡人皆要还之债，就是死亡
The debt that all men pay is death.
好的
All right.
L，A，B，O，U，L
L-A-B-O-U-L…
是Lab…ool…
It's Lab-ool…
Lab…ahl…La…
Lab-ahl… La…
哪儿来这么个词啊
It's gibberish.
- Laboulaye - 拉布莱伊
- Laboulaye！ - Laboulaye！
- 是什么？ - 是人名，爱德华・拉布莱伊
- What is that？ - It's a who. Edward Laboulaye.
电话在哪？
Where's the phone？
我不知道，这里乱的一塌糊涂
I don't know. Can't find anything in this mess.
- 只是暂时的，找到新地方我就搬走 - 还是找老地方吧，我喜欢她
- Temporary till I find a new place. - Find the old one. I like her.
- 嗨 - 蔡斯博士
- Hi. - Dr. Chase.
- 请叫我阿比盖尔 - 阿比盖尔
- Abigail, please. - Abigail.
- 幸会 - 请坐
- Nice to meet you. - Have a seat.
感谢你能来与我相见
Thanks for agreeing to meet with me.
别客气，关于那日记，我正想打电话给你
Of course. I was actually going to call you about the diary page.
- 有新的消息？ - 嗯…
- Any news？ - Well…
在上面发现了一些肉眼难辨的字母组合
We actually found some latent letter fragments on it.
你看
Take a look.
无意义的字母，是密码？
Random letters. A cipher？
- 也许 - 盖茨看过了吗？
- Maybe. - Gates seen this？
就是他发现的
He's the one that discovered it.
- 抱歉 - 没关系
- I'm sorry. - Not a problem.
- 请等我一分钟 - 请便
- I need one minute. - Please, take your time.
嘿，怎么了？
Hey. What？
我们破译了密码，明文是“拉布莱伊”
We cracked the cipher. It's "Laboulaye. "
密码的结果是“拉布莱伊”
The cipher spells "Laboulaye. "
拉布莱伊在法国是名人，这可能并不代表什么
So？ Laboulaye was well-known in France. It could be nothing.
也许如托马斯・盖茨所说，确实有张藏宝图
Or maybe there was a treasure map like Thomas Gates said there was,
而且藏宝图说不定就在拉布莱伊手上 后面还有一个单词，只有开头的部分
and Laboulaye had it. We only got a partial on the next word.
L，A，D，lad…ladder…
L- A-D, lad… ladder…
- L，A，D… - 阿拉丁，阿拉丁？
- L-A-D. - Aladdin！ Aladdin？
- Lady - 谢谢你，阿比盖尔
- Lady！ - Thank you, Abigail！
“拉布莱伊的女士” 你知道拉布莱伊曾策划过什么吗？
Laboulaye Lady. Do you know what Laboulaye was planning
就在林肯被暗杀期间
right around the time Lincoln was assassinated？
好了，本，我要挂了
OK, Ben, I've got to go.
藏宝图或藏宝图的线索就在神像上…
There's a map or a clue to a map on the Statue…
- 她挂了 - 她肯接你的电话，已经不错了
- She hung up. - She took your call. That was good.
- 盖茨博士 - 嗯
- Dr. Gates？ - Yes.
刚才我禁不住偷听了几句，他破译了密码？
Sounds like he cracked the cipher. I couldn't help but overhear.
拉布莱伊，是说爱德华・拉布莱伊？
Laboulaye？ As in Edouard Laboulaye？
他似乎是那么讲的
He seems to believe so, yes.
自由女神像就是根据他的想法建造的
Man who had the idea for the Statue of Liberty.
你说藏宝图在自由女神像上？
You're saying there's a treasure map in the Statue of Liberty？
拉布莱伊曾是个石匠，石匠喜欢 在自己的建筑作品中留下些线索
Laboulaye was a Mason. They built clues into everything.
是从我的书里读到的吧
Did you learn that from my book？
- 对历史有兴趣吗？ - 为之着迷
- Have an interest in history？ - Fascinated by it.
尤其是南北战争
Civil War, especially. My family's descended from
我家是南部邦联将军阿尔伯特・派克的后裔 他是个了不起的人物
Confederate General Albert Pike. He was a remarkable man.
历史不就是一尊伟人功绩的纪念碑吗？
But, then again, what is history but a marker for the deeds of great men？
凡人只有一世，但历史会永远铭记你
A man only has one lifetime, but history can remember you forever.
现在问题在于，是哪一座自由女神像？
So the only question is, which Statue of Liberty？
没错
Exactly.
还有第二座？
Is there more than one？
实际上有三座，莱利
There are three, actually, Riley.
一座在纽约，一座在卢森堡公园
One is in New York, one in the Luxembourg Garden.
但他只把其中的一座称为“女士”
But he only referred to one as his "lady. "
法国  巴黎
你的做法太不可思议了
This is like, impossible, what you're doing.
你的欣赏是我的荣幸
I'm glad you're enjoying it.
拉布莱伊一定在那上面留下了线索 去看看火炬
Laboulaye had to leave a clue somewhere on here. Move in on the torch.
让我来，这可不象看起来那么容易
Let me get there. It's not as easy as it looks.
我知道，我明白
No. Believe me, I understand.
抱歉，警官，什么事？
Excuse me, officer. May I help you？
美国人吧？
Ah, American, eh？
在你们看来也许没什么大不了的 但你们扰乱了其他人宁静的早晨
Of course you see no problem in disturbing everyone's pleasant morning
- 就是那个嗡嗡的东西 - 嘿
- with your buzzing there. - Hey！
多亏了你们法国人，才有我们国家的宪法 就是那个孟德斯鸠
You know how much our constitution was influenced by your man, Montesquieu？
- 你知道孟德斯鸠？ - 找到了
- You know Montesquieu？ - Got it.
孟德斯鸠，当然知道啦 “我们要建立一个政府…”
Montesquieu, yeah. "A government should be set up so that… "
“使人不必再惧怕他人”
"… no man need be afraid of another. "
- 说的好 - 谢谢
- That's very good. - Thank you.
- 我很吃惊呀 - 我找到了，找到了
- I'm astonished. - I got it, I got it.
- 希望你看得懂法语 - 我能帮忙吗？
- I hope you read French. - May I？
他可是警察啊
He's a cop.
“那双子远渡重洋，坚决…”
Um… "Across the sea these twins stand determined… "
- 坚定 - 坚定，对
- Resolute. - "Resolute," yeah.
“坚定屹立，守护我们的理想”
"… to preserve what we are looking for.
拉布莱伊，1876年
- Uh… Laboulaye, 1876." - Six.
- 这是线索 - 那双子坚定屹立着
- It's a clue. - "These twins stand resolute. "
我想想，坚定的双子
Let's see. Resolute twins.
坚定的
Resolute.
坚定的，而且是双子
Resolute. And then twins.
连体婴儿（连体和暹罗同字）？暹罗？ 是说法国与泰国间的航路吗？
Siamese twins？ Siam？ Trade routes between France and Thailand？
那绝对不可能… 英国皇家海军舰艇，坚定号
That's ridiculous. HMS Resolute.
19世纪时，这艘船曾在北冰洋失踪
A British ship that got lost in the Arctic in the 1800s.
后来这船被美国捕鲸船队发现 美国国会决定将其送还给英国
It was salvaged by American whalers, and then Congress sent it back to England.
这艘军舰退役之后
When the ship was finally retired,
维多利亚女王用船上的木料打造了两张书桌
Queen Victoria had two desks made from its timbers.
哇塞，坚定的双子
Voil？ Resolute twins.
- 那现在这两张桌子在哪儿？ - 较近的一张在伦敦
- And where are those desks now？ - The closest one is in London.
莱利，我们如何才能尽快到达白金汉宫？
How fast can we get to Buckingham Palace？
不知道，为什么不问问你的新朋友
Don't know. Why don't you ask your new best friend？
他会帮你叫出租车
He's going to call you a cab.
好吗？
OK？
- 这直升机很棒，是你的吗？ - 对，是我的
- Nice helicopter. Is that yours？ - Yes, actually. It is.
- 好吧，那罚单也是你的 - 太好了
- OK, so you get the ticket. - Great.
米奇・威尔金森在弗吉尼亚军事学院主修历史
Mitch Wilkinson studied history at Virginia Military Institute.
1978年毕业后他开了一家私人保安公司 海湾战争时公司在伊拉克执行过保安任务
Graduated 1978. Ran a private security company which had contracts in Iraq
90年代后期还曾在刚果接了一笔单子
during the invasion, and in the Congo in the late '90s.
他不仅是一名资深雇佣兵 同时还是一个黑市古董商
These are trained mercenaries as well as being black-market antiquities dealers.
一个黑市古董商为什么会 捐献弥足珍贵的南北战争文物呢？
So why does a black market antiquities dealer give up a rare Civil War artifact？
完全可以卖给私人收藏家大赚一笔
Something he could sell to a private collector for a good deal of money？
设备1克隆设备2
正在传输…正在接收
设备克隆已完成
英国  伦敦
女王办公室在这里
So the queen's office is here.
升降机能带你上去
The elevator shaft gets you close,
但是唯一的通道要经过保安室
but the only direct access is through security.
- 真够刺激的 - 得想法子让你先进那房间
- That should be exciting. - We got to get you in that room.
- 嗨，爸爸 - 本
- Hi, Dad. - Ben.
是帕特里克・盖茨打给本的电话
It's Patrick Gates' phone. He's calling Ben.
给我吧
Give me that.
昨晚有人闯进我们家，我被袭击了
The house was broken into last night. I was attacked.
快报警，我这就回来
Call the police. I'm coming home.
- 怎么了？发生什么事了？ - 那于事无补啊
- What？ - What good would that do？
他们什么都没拿，我也没事
They didn't take anything. And besides, I'm fine.
好吧，我们在伦敦，正准备去白金汉宫
OK. We're in London. We're going to Buckingham Palace.
明天下午我们和管理人还有约会
We have an appointment with the curator tomorrow afternoon.
- 好的，儿子，小心点，再见 - 再见
- Son, just be careful. Goodbye. - Bye.
还有其他人在打宝藏的主意
Someone else is after the treasure.
那是肯定的
Of course someone else is after the treasure.
- 这是寻宝行业的金科玉律 - 我们必须赶快去看那桌子
- It's the axiom of treasure hunting. - We have to hurry and see that desk.
我们可不能错过那个约会哦
We don't want to miss that appointment.
- 嗨，我是本・盖茨 - 西翼安全公司的吧，请进
- Hi. Ben Gates. - See security. They'll let you in.
好，午茶时间到了，伙计们
OK. It's teatime, chaps.
我在找管理人办公室，应该怎么走？
Looking for the curator's office. Which way was it again？
顺着楼梯上去，第一条过道左转
Follow the stairs round, then turn first left.
非常感谢
Thank you so much.
- 本 - 阿比盖尔
- Ben. - Abigail.
- 她怎么在这儿？ - 你怎么在这儿？
- What's she doing here？ - What're you doing？
你爸爸打电话跟我说的 你的下一条线索在这里
Your dad called me. Said your next clue was here.
- 真的是她？ - 本…
- She's really there？ - Ben…
- 甩掉她，摆脱她 - 我想来帮忙
- Drop her. Lose her. - I want to help.
太好了，但现在不是时候
That's very nice, but it's a bad time right now.
- 现在不是时候？ - 对，不是时候
- A bad time, right now？ - It's a bad time.
那好，我大老远的飞到伦敦来帮你
OK, I just flew all the way to London to offer my help…
- 别忘了计划 - 你却不需要？
- Remember the plan. - You don't need it？
你是想来吵架的？
You're the one making a scene.
- 我现在没想跟你吵 - 我们倒是需要吵一吵
- I… I'm not making a scene right now. - We want to make a scene.
那好吧，如果你想吵，那就吵
Well then, fine！ If that's what you want, let's have it out now！
- 太狡猾了 - 我猜猜？是时机不对？
- So subtle. - Let me guess？ It's the wrong time.
还是地方不对？反正又是我的错！
It's the wrong place. I'm wrong again！
我俩的事是我的错 托马斯・盖茨也是我的错
Wrong about us, wrong about Thomas Gates,
以为你会喜欢安娜女王式的椅子 也是我的错！
wrong that you'd like the Queen Anne chair！
你错就错在自认为我喜欢那椅子
You're wrong to assume I'd like the chair.
大家听见没，都来听听 这比导游讲的好听多了
You see？ Everybody, listen to this. This is more interesting than that.
她觉得就算我做对了，也是错 有这道理吗？
She thinks that even when I'm right, I'm wrong！ Isn't that right？
阿比盖尔，如果遇到问题时我抢答了
Abigail, just because I answer a question quickly
那也算是错吗？
doesn't make it wrong.
需要我们两人一起做决定的时候 即使你一个人做对了，那也是错
Not if the answer's something we need to figure out as a couple.
- 两人相处就该这样 - 先生
- That's what couples do！ - Sir.
能请你和这位小姐，去外面解决吗？
You and your missis, take it outside.
看看你都干了什么，你把小警察都招来了
Now look what you've done. You've brought the little bobbies down on us！
你把这位小姐带出去吧，我要留在这
You take the missis outside. I'm staying right here.
本
- Ben！ - Whee！
- 下午好，先生 - （学英国口音）你好
- Good afternoon, sir. - Hello.
- 喝酒了，是吧？ - 就一点
- Been drinking, have we？ - Just a nip.
到酒吧喝了那么一品脱而已，没事的
Popped down to the pub for a pint！ Bit of all right！
因为我喜欢威士忌，就要拘捕我？
Going to arrest a man for that？Going to detain a blighter for enjoying his whiskey？
- 够了 - 香肠炖薯泥
- Enough. - Bangers and mash.
土豆炒包菜，烟熏烤鳗派
Bubbles and squeak. Smoked eel pie.
- 先生 - 杂碎八宝菜
- Sir！ - Haggis！
- 够了，给我下来 - 我还买了一大堆椰子！
- That's it！ Dismount the banister！ - I've got a lovely bunch of coconuts！
它们就在那儿，排排坐呀…
Here they are, standing in a row！
小个的，大个的，有的就像你脑袋那么大
Small ones, big ones, some as big as your head！
太有才了
That was brilliant.
- 作出正确的决定也有错？ - 没错，你也该试着去正确一次
- What's wrong with being right？ - Nothing. You should try it sometime.
- 你是说我从来没做对过？ - 我可没那么说
- You're saying that I'm never right？ - I did not say that.
那我是不是又错了？
Hoo！ So I'm wrong again.
- 瞧瞧，你总算对一次了 - 好得很啊，妙到巅啊
- Now, see, there you are correct. - Capital. Topper.
你妈妈早跟我说过了
Your mother told me about you.
- 进去 - 那你为什么不干脆列个清单呢
- In here, please. - Why don't you just make a list
上面写好我能说什么，不能说什么
of what's OK for me to say or not write something…
- 每次都是你自己独自判断对错 - 你们两只唧喳鸟，待在这儿吧
- What's right or wrong… - You two, stay.
- 好吗？ - 别，不要，伙计
- Right？ - No！ No, no, man.
- 别把我关在这儿 - 哇哦
- Don't leave me in here！ - That's great. Wow.
怎么回事情？
What is going on？
很抱歉把你也卷进来 但你的表演真得很棒
I'm sorry for getting you roped into this, but you were excellent.
- 承蒙夸奖，你也不赖 - 你是什么时候察觉的？
- Thank you. So were you. - When did you figure out
- 察觉我是假装和你吵的？ - 就在我们假吵的时候…
- it was a fake argument？ - When'd you figure out I was
- 你什么时候察觉到我是真在和你吵？ - 就是吵到一半的时候
- arguing during the fake argument？ - The middle.
你说我自以为是的时候… 莱利，快让我们出去
Where "I assume I'm right. " Get us out. Which I don't get.
我不明白为什么我自认为是对的 并做对了之后却仍然是错的
If I'm right, after I assume I'm right, then I'm correct.
你没有问我就私自决定
When you get to a conclusion without asking,
而你又碰巧做对的话，那不过是你走运而已
and you happen to be right, you got lucky.
那看来我总是走运
I get lucky a lot.
那么，你当我是摆设咯，本？
So where does that leave me, Ben？
你们俩实在是绝配啊
You guys are so great together.
- 想知道我为什么要来这儿吗？ - 当然
- Want to know why I'm here？ - Uh-huh.
我认为女王书房的坚定之桌里可能有线索
Think there may be a clue on the Resolute desk in the queen's study.
明白没有？
Does that help？
我就不明白为什么对你来说 和别人一起做决定会那么难
Don't understand why it's difficult for you to include others in your decisions.
即使你能猜到我的回答
Just because you may know what my answer is going to be
也不代表你就可以不问我啊
doesn't mean you don't have to ask me.
一号门，开启中
Door number one, opening.
好吧，我们来试试看
OK. Let me try this out.
阿比盖尔，请你跟我一起去好吗
Abigail, would you like to come with me, please？
好的，谢谢
Yes. Thank you.
搞笑，你得留在这儿
Ridiculous. You're staying.
- 太危险了 - 那我也要去
- It's too dangerous. - I am so coming.
- 二号门 - 二号门，马上好
- Door number two. - Door two, coming up.
- 你不准去 - 那你叫保安啊
- You're not coming. - Call security.
你应该就在升降梯旁边了
You should be near a service elevator.
你干嘛？送花给女王吗？
What are you doing？ Are those for the queen？
女王不在这，王旗没有升起 所以女王应该在温莎堡
Queen's not here. There's no flag flying. Queen's at Windsor.
- 你想干嘛？ - 去看看桌子，不带你，再见
- What are you doing？ - See the desk, without you.
- 不 - 别让她去
- No. - Don't let her go.
阿比盖尔…
Abigail…
好吧，进来，快进来
All right. Get in. Get in. Get in！
拿着
Hold this.
请把花还给我好吗？
Will you give me the flowers back, please？
嗯
Yeah.
- 怎么了？ - 你擦了我送你的香水
- What？ - Wearing the perfume I bought you.
那又如何？
So？
那让我闻到了美女的芬芳
So I think it smells kind of pretty.
- 那是花香，本 - 不，不是
- It's the flowers, Ben. - No, it's not.
我们走
Let's go.
好的，现在左转
OK, now turn left.
- 死路 - 我是说向右，右转
- Dead end. - I mean right. Go right.
- 这花…花瓣…花蕊… - 好，很好
- The flowers… petals… stamens. - Good. Good.
快走，进去
Go, go.
那就是了
That's it.
坚定之桌
The Resolute desk.
我们要找的是…
We're looking for…
镌刻的文字或者图案，或者其它什么的
…writing, patterns in the carvings. Could be anything.
看这个
Hey, look at this.
- 马尔科姆・吉尔瓦里，1880年 - 等一下
- "Malcolm Gilvary, 1880." - Hold on one second.
找到了，马尔科姆・吉尔瓦里，他不是做家具的
Here we go. Malcolm Gilvary. He didn't make furniture.
他是做中国秘盒的
He made Chinese puzzle boxes.
怎么了？
- Oh… - What？
我认为这抽屉的工作原理和 保险箱上的密码筒类似
I think these drawers work like tumblers in a safe.
好吧，4张抽屉就是4位阿拉伯数字组合
OK, four drawers… Four-digit combination？
会是年份吗？
What about a year？
我看看，维多利亚女王，生于1819年
Uh, let me see. Queen Victoria, born 1819.
那就是一
So you go one…
八
Eight.
一
One.
九
Nine.
- 对不对？ - 巴黎女神像火炬上刻的是1876，试试看
- Any luck？ - OK… 1876 was on the inscription on the statue in Paris. Let's try that.
一
One.
八
Eight.
七
Seven.
六
Six.
新问题来了
New rules.
这图案，像是印加或阿兹特克的文字
These markings, like Incan or Aztec.
我之前从来没见过类似的符号
I have never seen any symbols like this.
这看起来比南北战争可要古老的多
I mean, this looks centuries older than Civil War.
你觉得这上面是什么意思？
What do you think it means？
我怀疑这东西跟暗杀林肯计划有关
I doubt it has anything to do with the plot to assassinate Lincoln.
警报，警报，本，快离开
Mayday. Mayday. Ben, get out of there.
- 那两个被拘者去哪了？ - 好，来点响动如何
- Oi！ Where are my detainees？ - OK, let's make some noise.
火警响了
The fire alarm's gone off.
老天保佑女王
Uh-oh. God save the queen.
所有人请撤离
All units, go to action zebra.
- 怎么了？ - 还不清楚
- What's going on？ - Haven't the foggiest.
肯定是什么人或者什么东西触发的
Someone or something is causing this.
- 各单位检查各自区域 - 没有道理啊
- Check your primary stations. - This doesn't make any sense.
找出信号源，检查公众四区，八区
Find the source terminal and check public areas four and eight.
女士们，先生这边走 谢谢合作，请继续向前走
This way, ladies and gentlemen. Thank you very much. Keep moving.
一直走到喷泉那边
Keep walking until you're on the other side of the fountain.
- 请原谅，请原谅，让一让 - 找到他们了，他们在正门
- Excuse me, excuse me. Coming through. - I got them. They're at the main gate.
- “火花”，别这样 - 好了，我们走
- Oi！ Sparkle. Come on. - OK. Here we go.
我对狗有些过敏
I'm a little bit allergic.
- 谢谢，好了 - 莱利
- Riley. - Thank you. OK.
- 回头见，谢谢，再见 - 坐下，对不起
- See you later. Thank you. Bye-bye. - Sit！ Sorry！
谢谢你们等我，东西能让我看看吗？
Thanks for waiting for me. Can I see the thing？
丹尼尔，等等
Daniel, hold it.
那是什么？
What is that？
到白金汉宫就为了这块木头？
Went to Buckingham Palace, all I got was this wood？
看看这些符号，以前从来没见过
Look at the symbols. Never seen anything like this.
这是个不可思议的大发现
It's an incredible discovery.
- 威尔金森 - 拦住他们，快，快
- Wilkinson. - Stop them. Go, go, go！
- 那个打宝藏主意的家伙就是他 - 我来开车
- He's the one after the treasure. - I'll drive.
这可是英国
We're in England.
有枪，快趴下
It's a gun！ Get down！
- 我们被困住了 - 趴下，把头低下
- We're trapped！ - Hang on！ Keep your heads down.
你是谁？
Hey, who are you？
抱歉
Sorry.
- 本，他们追上来了 - 他们想怎么样啊？
- Ben, they're getting closer. - What is their problem？
- 左转，左转 - 抓紧
- Go left！ Go left！ - Hold on.
转弯，转弯
Turn, turn！
小心
Watch out！
大家没事吧？
Everybody OK？
- 快，快点 - 丹尼，让他们停下
- Come on, come on. - Danny, I want them stopped.
小心
Look out！
快，快，快，快
Go. Go, go, go, go！
看到他往哪跑了吗？
Did you see where he went？
- 什么声音？ - 有人电话响，是他打来的
- What is that？ Someone's phone. - It's him.
- 你的号码簿里有他的号码？ - 你闭…
- Have his number in your speed dial？ - Oh, shu…
趁还没人受伤，及早收手吧
This has to end before someone gets hurt.
把你在白金汉宫拿到的东西给我 就不会有人受伤
Give me what you got at Buckingham, it won't be necessary.
跟我父亲去说吧
Tell that to my father.
白痴
Moron！
他们干嘛站在路中央
Why are they standing in the middle of the street？
- 这些人要去哪？ - 为什么每个人都在跑？
- Where are these people going？ - Why's everyone running？
- 他就在后面，快 - 快开
- He's right there！ Go！ - Move！
让开！
Get out of the way！
- 我好像压到谁的脚了 - 小心人群
- Did I just run over a man's foot？ - Watch the people！
快，快，快点
Go！ Go！ Faster！
- 就在那儿 - 看到他们了
- Right over there. - I got them.
- 他们还跟着我们 - 这手机能拍照吗？
- They're still behind us. - This phone have a camera？
- 不能拍，手机坏了 - 好吧，把木板给我
- No. No, it's broken. - All right. Give me the plank.
坐稳，我们要闯红灯了
Hang on. We're going to run a red light.
侵入伦敦警局的数据库 找出交通探头拍的照片
Hack into the London Police database and get a picture from that traffic cam.
- 知道啦老大 - 怎么，你不行吗？
- Okey-dokey. - You can't do it？
我行的，我就是不喜欢你自以为我行
No, I can. I just don't like that you assume that I can.
谢谢你，莱利
Why, thank you, Riley.
去拿
Get it！
停车，停车
Stop！ Stop！
- 他拿到了 - 是什么东西？
- He's got it. - What is it？
不知道，但是归我们了，走
I don't know, but it's ours. Let's go.
华盛顿特区
- 阿比盖尔 - 嘿，帕特里克
- Abigail！ - Hey, Patrick.
真高兴看见你们俩又在一起了
Nice to see you two together again.
- 嗯，其实我们没有 - 嗯
- Yeah, well, we're not. - Yeah.
我还以为能把这些箱子弄出去了呢
Oh, I was hoping to get some of these boxes out of the house.
我看不太懂这玩意
I can't read the whole thing, but I can tell you that
但我告诉你们，这些文字肯定是 在殖民时代之前的美洲土著留下的
these are definitely pre-colonial Native American markings.
- 历史远不止500年 - 远远不止
- Easily 500 years old. - Easily.
我认得其中一个符号
I can identify one symbol.
看看这个，你知道那是什么吗？
Look at this. Do you know what that is？
宗教历法？我不知道
Sacred calendrical？ I don't know.
那个符号是“锡沃拉”
That symbol is Cibola.
“锡沃拉”
That's Cibola.
就是黄金之城
The City of Gold.
黄金之城
1527年，一艘西班牙船在佛罗里达海岸失事
"In 1527, a Spanish ship wrecked on the Florida coast.
只有四人生还
There were only four survivors.
其中一个是名叫埃斯特班的奴隶 他救了当地部落酋长一命
One was a slave named Esteban who saved a local tribe's dying chief.
作为回报，他被带到部落的圣城
As a reward, he was taken to their sacred city,
一座由黄金打造的城市
a city built from solid gold.
后来，埃斯特班想重新找到这座城市 但再也没能找到
Later, when Esteban tried to find the city again, he never could.
但这故事却越传越广，每个来到新大陆的 探险家都在寻找这城市
But the legend grew, and every explorer came to the New World in search of it.
1876年，当卡斯特将军一班寻宝人马 在小巨角被土著全歼之后
When General Custer's search for gold ended with his last stand
寻找黄金城的最后一丝希望也破灭了
at Little Bighorn, it became clear none would ever find it. "
本，想想看，如果南方邦联找到黄金城…
Ben, can you imagine if the Confederates got their hands on the City of Gold…
天啊
My God.
我要找她谈谈
I'm going to go talk to her.
- 你也一起去 - 不！
- You're coming with me. - No！
- 除了她没有别人能翻译这个 - 有其他人选的
- Hey. No one else can translate it. - There are others.
有好几个其他人选呢
There are several others.
说到古代美洲土著文明，没人比她更合适了
For ancient Native American？ No one better.
- 说谁啊？ - 瞧，本，我不能和你一起去
- Who？ - Look, Ben, I can't go with you.
- 已经，已经25年了 - 32年了
- It's been, what？ Twenty-five years. - Thirty-two.
有那么久了？
That long？
之所以我们32年没有说过话是有原因的
There's a reason why we haven't spoken in 32 years.
- 我们根本没有共通之处 - 那我呢？
- We have nothing in common. - Me？
当然啦，我肯定她和我一样，都以你为傲
Yes, of course. And I'm sure she's just as proud of you as I am.
- 谁啊？ - 他妈妈
- Who？ - His mom.
马里兰大学
- 放松点好吗？没事的 - 当然啦，是该往好的方面想
- Will you relax？ It's gonna be fine. - Sure. Should look at the bright side.
过去那么久了，也许她失忆了，不认得我了
Been a long time. Maybe she lost her memory, won't recognize me.
我恨她！
I hate her！
没错就是这儿了
We're in the right place.
我可不想趟这汪浑水
I'm gonna take myself out of the line of fire for this one.
- 嗨，妈妈 - 本杰明
- Hi, Mom. - Benjamin！
阿比盖尔，好一个惊喜啊，你好，亲爱的
Abigail！ What a surprise！ Hello, sweetheart.
看见没？就一个叹词，心里藏着刀呢
You see？ One syllable, a knife in the heart.
- 不至于吧 - 她做得出来
- Oh, no. - She can do that.
正好借这机会问问，我那两把牙刷的下落
I can also track the whereabouts of my toothbrush.
不是我把牙刷丢在马拉喀什的
I was not the one that left the toothbrushes in Marrakech.
照你说的，我把它们都放到旅行包里了
I stowed them both in the travel case, as instructed.
对，但是你坚持要负责把行李放上车的
Yes, and you also insisted on loading the luggage into the taxi.
- 我没坚持，而且我的确把行李放上车了 - 对，但你没有拿旅行包
- Didn't insist. I loaded the luggage. - Not the travel case.
旅行包不是行李箱好不好 包应该是打在行李箱里的
Travel case is not luggage. The case goes into the luggage.
- 是谁负责打包行李的呢？ - 我没法把旅行包装进行李箱
- Who was in charge of packing？ - I couldn't get the case into
因为里面塞了你买的蠢毯子
the luggage. It was full with that stupid rug you bought.
你以为上面绣有某种秘密
You thought it had secret stitching.
- 你说那有多蠢？ - 那上面的确绣有秘密
- How stupid was that？ - Did have stitching.
- 六只绿色假皮皮箱… - 妈妈
- Six phony green leather suitcases… - Mom.
我需要你帮忙看下这个
I need you to take a look at this.
- 这是什么照片？ - 这东西很有意思
- What is that a picture of？ - It's interesting.
- 我们认为可能是奥尔麦克文字（奥尔麦克：墨西哥东南的神秘古印第安种族） - 是的
- We think it might be Olmec. - It is.
是索克语没错，不过更古老
Yes, yes, definitely proto-Zoquean.
我们希望你能翻译一下
We were hoping that you could translate it.
嗯，你们肯定是为了这个才来的
Yes, of course you were.
这不会又跟寻宝有关吧，是不是？
Oh, this doesn't involve another treasure hunt, does it？
妈妈，这个确实非常重要
Mom, this is actually very important.
好吧，看看有些什么
All right. What have we got here？
这个…这个象形字…意思是“鸟” 那个么…
This… this glyph here, that means "bird. " And that means…
恩，是尊鸟
Uh, "noble bird. "
尊鸟有缘，伸手相牵 圣殿已近，路在眼前
"Find the noble bird, let him take you by the hand and give you passage to the sacred temple. "
你们认为这是黄金城的藏宝图，是吧？
Oh, you think this is a treasure map for Cibola, don't you？
嗯，正是如此
Well, that is exactly what it is.
不，那个符号不是指黄金城 而是指世界的中心
No, this glyph doesn't mean "Cibola. " It means "the center of the world. "
你以前很喜欢这个的 她就是在寻宝的路途中爱上我的
You know, you used to like it. She fell in love with me on a treasure hunt.
那不是爱情，是冲动，肾上腺素加上龙舌兰酒
That was not love. That was excitement, adrenaline and tequila.
- 妈妈… - 我不过是想拿到学分而已
- Mom… - I was trying to get course credit.
除非你最近不看书不读报 你该知道寻宝是有回报的
Treasure hunting paid off, in case you haven't read the papers.
但那跟你没什么关系，是本干的
Had nothing to do with you. That was Ben.
本发现了宝藏，你什么都没干
Ben found the treasure. You did nothing.
帕特里克，艾米丽，别吵了 我们专心解译古文吧？
Patrick, Emily, please. Can we just figure out what's on the page？
就这么多了，恐怕帮不了你们
Well, that's it, I'm afraid.
这些象形文字少了一部分 你们只拿到了一半藏宝图
These glyphs are only partials. So you only have half a treasure map.
我很遗憾
I'm sorry.
我倒不是很惊讶
Not that I'm surprised.
至少我们知道其余的部分在哪
At least we know where the rest of the map is.
什么？
What？
你知道在哪？那你为什么不告诉我
You know where it is？ Why didn't you tell me？
原因很简单，你这个人容易反应过度
Obviously you have a tendency to overreact！
- 对不起 - 我也是
- I'm sorry. - So am I.
那究竟在哪儿呢？
So where is it？
巴黎的雕像上铭写着 “双子坚定的屹立”
Inscription on the statue in Paris said, "These twins stand resolute. "
我们认为地图被分藏在两张坚定之桌内
We think the map's divided between the two Resolute desks.
坚定之桌…就是那张坚定之桌？
The Resolute desk. The Resolute desk？
总统的书桌？
President's desk？
总统，什么总统？
The president. What president？
- 是我们的总统么？ - 很不幸，就是他
- Our president？ - Unfortunately, yes.
如此一来…
But that means…
这么说，那我们就得…
Wait, so we have to…
去白宫？
The White House？
确切的说，是去总统办公室
The Oval Office… to be exact.
我怎么可能会对这个反应过度呢？
Why would I overreact to that？
- 我们事先约定的不是这个 - 请你专心处理眼前的问题好吗？
- That's not what I signed on for. - Could we focus on the issue at hand？
谢谢
Thank you.
年代很久远，早于哥伦布时期
It's early, pre-Columbian.
- 你能翻译吗？ - 别开玩笑了
- Can you translate it？ - Are you kidding？
这是一种极其罕见的已经失传的语言
This is an extinct, exceedingly rare language.
只有极少数一些人在研究这些语言
Only a handful of people study these languages.
如何找到那些人？
Where are we to find them？
在大学里也许能找到人 但你拿到的东西不完整
Universities, I suppose. But you don't have the whole thing.
什么意思？
What do you mean？
这些象形字被切断了
These glyphs here… they're cut off.
还有其它地图？我们去哪找？
There's more to the map？ How are we going to find that？
我们不用找，盖茨会去找的
We won't have to. Gates will get it somehow.
坚定之桌的位置靠着总统办公室的南墙
The Resolute desk is near the south wall in the Oval Office.
看这个，看
Look at this. Look.
桌子的正面有扇小门
Small door on the front of the desk.
罗斯福装的，想遮掩他的轮椅
FDR had that put in so guests couldn't see his wheelchair.
- 但是… - 伙计们，看下这个
- But… - Guys, take a look at this.
这也许能行
This could work.
阿比盖尔，该和你的新男友来一次约会了
I believe it's time for you to make a date with your new boyfriend.
说的没错
I think you're right.
欢迎参加白宫复活节滚蛋赛
We hope you're enjoying the White House Easter Egg Roll.
两点钟在南边喷泉有脸谱彩绘
Face painting continues at 2:00 near the south fountain.
- 那只大兔子是康纳扮的吗？ - 谢谢
- That Connor in the bunny suit？ - Thank you.
我没参加过滚蛋赛，满有趣的
I've never been to an Easter Egg Roll. It's kind of sweet.
嗯，我也很喜欢
Yeah, I love it.
我认识你，你的曾曾祖父杀了林肯总统
I know you. Your great-great-grandfather killed President Lincoln.
不，那是约翰・威尔克斯・布斯干的
No. That would be John Wilkes Booth.
艾森施密尔说布斯是受人指使
Eisenschiml says that Booth was a tool
这个惊天阴谋还牵涉到林肯的内阁成员
in a greater conspiracy that involved men in Lincoln's Cabinet.
胡说！艾森施密尔的书里…
Absurd. Eisenschiml's book is filled with
- 尽是些不实的研究和错误的假设 - 哦，是吗？
- spotty research and false assumptions. - Oh, yeah？
那晚林肯的保镖擅离职守，怎么解释？
Explain why Lincoln's bodyguard left his post that night？
因为林肯总统去戏院时从来不带保镖
Because President Lincoln was never accompanied by guards
尤其是在美好的周五晚上，听到没有？
when attending the theater. Listening？ Especially on Good Friday.
那晚华盛顿所有出城道路都被封锁了
Explain why all the bridges out of Washington were closed
唯独只有布斯出逃的那条路没封锁 这你又怎么解释？
except one, the one Booth needed to escape？
走开，讨厌的小鬼，快走
OK, run along now, you impossible child. Run along.
美国的教育究竟是怎么了？
What is going on with the education in America？
- 嘿，嘿 - 康纳
- Hey！ Hey！ - Connor！
你终于来了，我很高兴
- I'm so glad you decided to come… - Hey.
- …盖茨也来了啊 - 康纳
…with Gates. - Connor.
- 我们碰巧遇上 - 哦
- We just ran into each other. - Oh.
你不是有事要问他吗？
Aren't you going to ask him？
- 问我什么？ - 没什么
- Ask me what？ - Nothing.
- 不，好好说，要问什么？ - 我实在不想强人所难
- No, really. What？ - I really wouldn't want to impose.
她的意思是，她认为你做不到
Well, what she means is she doesn't think you can.
- 认为我做不到什么？ - 她想参观总统办公室
- Doesn't think I can what？ - She wants to see the Oval Office.
- 不，我知道这要求太过分了 - 这没什么
- No. That is way too much to ask. - No, it's, uh…
- 我能搞定 - 真的吗？
- I can do that. - Really？
我说的吧
You see？
- 你真的可以？ - 嗯
- You can？ - Yeah.
那太棒了，我一直都想看看总统办公室
That is so cool, Connor. I have always wanted to see the Oval Office.
康纳真牛
Connor rocks.
我们到了
Well… here we are.
帝王般的家具，锯齿状的装饰，我就喜欢！
Empire furnishings and crenelated molding. Love it.
站在这房中，感觉真奇妙，是不是？
Amazing feeling, isn't it, standing in here？
- 是啊，太棒了 - 你…
- Yes. Amazing, huh？ - Oh, could…
对不起
Oh. Sorry.
那是坚定之桌
Oh, that's, uh… The Resolute desk.
你可能看过肯尼迪小儿子那张知名照片
Might recognize it from the photo of young JFK Junior
趁他父亲办公时在下面玩
playing underneath while his father was working.
- 令人惊叹啊 - 嗯
- Wonderful. - Yeah.
但是很多人不知道
But many people don't know
在白金汉宫里有张一模一样的桌子
that this desk has a twin that sits in Buckingham Palace.
- 真有此事？ - 谁会知道这个啊？
- Isn't that something？ - Who knew？
从拉瑟福德・海斯开始（拉瑟福德・海斯：1877～1880年在任）
Every president since Rutherford B. Hayes
每一任总统都用过那张桌子 除了约翰逊和尼克松之外
has used that desk, except, uh, Johnson and Nixon.
还有福特也没用过
And Ford, of course.
- 他用过的 - 他没用过
- Uh, no. - Uh, yes.
- 用过的 - 没用过
- No. - Yes.
阿比盖尔，你是不是掉了一只耳环？
Abigail！ Did you lose an earring？
哦，我…我真弄丢了一只
Oh！ I… I did, yes.
康纳，那耳环是我祖母给我的
Connor, these were given to me by my grandmother.
我想我们该四处找一下 你不会希望有人发现
I suppose we should look for it. Wouldn't want anyone finding an earring
不属于第一夫人的耳环吧？
that doesn't belong to the first lady in the Oval Office.
- 对 - 说的好
- Yes. - Excellent point,
我们不该出现在这儿的…
considering we're not supposed to be here.
- 嗯 - 我们不如就从那里开始找吧？
- Yeah. - Why don't we, um, go over here and check it out？
我在这儿找
I'll check over here.
- 你认为会不会掉到下面去了 - 嗯
- Do you think it fell down here？ - Yes.
- 也可能在这儿 - 有可能
- Maybe here. - Probably.
哦，没有
Oh, no.
- 你刚才坐过沙发 - 那些大兔子
- You did sit on the sofa. - Oh, the bunnies.
康纳
Connor！
- 你找到了 - 是我找到的
- You found it. - I did.
非常感谢
Thank you so much！
你是最棒的
You're just the best. Mm.
谢谢
Thank you.
没什么
OK.
- 那里是空的 - 一定被人拿走了
- Empty. - Someone must've taken it.
我们国家最聪明的一群人 在那桌前坐了一百多年了
Brightest men in our country sat at that desk for over a hundred years.
- 看看这个 - 其中肯定有人发现了地图
- Look. - Course one of 'em found the map.
- 木头上有一个标记 - 是总统的印章吧
- A symbol stamped into the wood. - The presidential seal.
这不是总统的印章
It's not the presidential seal.
图中这只鹰抓的是卷轴，而不是橄榄树枝
The eagle's holding a scroll instead of olive branches.
- 我不敢确定这是什么意思 - 我们怎么办
- I'm not sure what this is. - What do we do？
你们当中就没人读过我的书吗？
Did none of you read my book？
持卷之鹰
The eagle clutching the scroll.
- 你知道这代表什么？ - 嗯
- Do you know what it means？ - Yeah.
但我没法用三言两语说清楚
But it's not something I could tell you.
只好借我的书来让你们明白了
It's something that I have to show you… in my book.
- 你连信壳都没拆？ - 我不是正在搬家嘛
- You didn't even open it？ - I was moving.
第13章
Chapter 13.
- “总统秘卷”？ - “总统秘卷”
- "The President's Secret Book"？ - "The President's Secret Book. "
这是一本由历任总统亲撰，在总统间 代代相传的档案辑，只有总统才能看
It happens to be a collection of documents for presidents by presidents, and for presidents' eyes only.
伙计们，我说的不仅仅是约翰・肯尼迪
And I'm not just talking about JFK here, guys.
水门事件中神秘消失的十八又半分钟录音
The 18 and a half missing minutes of the Watergate tapes.
阿波罗号是否真的登月了？是真是假？
Did the Apollo really land on the moon？ Did it？ Did it？
还有世人最为好奇的，51区（51区：传说中研究外星人的秘密基地）
And the coup de grce… Area 51.
拜托，莱利，那些不过是民间传说
Come on, Riley. That's… that's an urban legend.
真的吗，阿比盖尔？是这样吗？
Is it, Abigail？ Is it？
这些实在是太…
It's just totally…
- 疯狂？ - 对
- Crazy？ - Yeah.
我们就是靠着疯狂，才有了今天啊
Hm. 'Cause last time I checked, we pretty much make our living on crazy.
- 他说的对 - 我想是吧
- He's got a point. - I guess so.
一样的图案
Same symbol.
1966年因资讯公开法而公之于众
Released in '66 under the Freedom of Information Act.
鹰和卷轴
The eagle and the scroll,
总统秘卷的专属标记
the secret symbol in the President's Book.
你的意思是，那块木板上的内容
So you're saying that whatever was on that plank
现在应该在总统秘卷里？
is now in the President's Secret Book？
本
Ben.
如果换作是你想说服我的话
If it was you trying to convince me…
即使你没什么证据，我也一样会信你
…you'd have less evidence, and I'd already believe you by now.
持卷之鹰？
The eagle with the scroll？
阴谋论者相信
Conspiracy theorists like to believe
这是总统秘卷的标记
that it's the symbol for the President's Secret Book.
你竟然买了莱利的书
You bought Riley's book.
你的朋友写了本关于政府阴谋的书
Your friend writes a book about government conspiracies.
- 你以为我们会不知道？ - 但这是真的吗？
- You don't think we know about it？ - But is it true？
总统真的有一本秘卷吗？
Does the president have a secret book？
喜欢鸭子吗？
Do you like ducks？
确实有这么一本书
There is a book.
你为什么要出来告诉我？
Why are you telling me out here？
因为在里面，我是名联邦探员
Because inside, I'm a federal agent.
在外面，我是作为一名朋友和你谈话
Out here, I'm talking to you as a friend.
- 那么总统秘卷保存在哪儿呢？ - 只有现任总统才知道
- Where's the President's Book kept？ - Only the current president knows.
这本书是由总统代代相传的
The book is passed from president to president,
每一任都亲自选择藏书的地点
and each one chooses his own hiding place.
你是FBI，能帮我找到它吗？
You're the FBI. Can't you get it for me？
要看那本书的唯一途径就是成为总统
Only way you'll ever see that book is if you get elected president.
世事难料啊
Well, you never know.
我只需要接近他几分钟就行
All I need is a few minutes with him.
几分钟？真的？
A few minutes？ Really？
就算你嫁给了总统
Even if you were married to the president,
都不一定能和他待上几分钟
you wouldn't be able to get a few minutes.
他身边有人的话，当然不行 如果我能和单独见到他…
Not when he's surrounded by handlers. If I get him alone…
你怎么可能单独和总统见面？
How do you expect to get the president alone？
南北战争之前，各州分立
Before the Civil War, the states were all separate.
人们称之为“众国”
People used to say, "The United States are. " Are
直到内战结束后，人们方称之为“合众国”
Wasn't until the war ended people started saying, "The United States is. "
是林肯让我们的国家从分裂走向统一
Under Lincoln… we became one nation.
而林肯为此付出了生命代价
And Lincoln paid for it with his life.
- 托马斯・盖茨也是如此 - 对
- So did Thomas Gates. - Right.
以身报国
With his life.
我要如何才能与他单独相处呢？
So how am I gonna get him alone？
我要绑架他
I'm gonna kidnap him.
我要绑架美国总统
I'm gonna kidnap the president of the United States.
- 这可不好笑 - 我是你父亲
- That's not funny. - I'm your father.
你要我说什么？你不能自毁前程
How do you expect me to respond？ I can't let you ruin your life.
你疯了吗？
Are you out of your mind？
读了我的书就知道，你没机会拿到秘卷
Read my book, and you'd know you can't get to that book.
你究竟打算怎么干？
Exactly how do you plan on doing this？
弗农山庄（华盛顿故居）
- I was thinking Mount Vernon. - Oh.
- 什么？ - 我加入
- What？ - I'm in.
长官，我们必须更改宴会的地点
Sir, we have to move the party.
白宫新闻厅
某个历史学家说，斯宾塞地标大酒店…
Some historian claims the Spencer Landmark Hotel
在19世纪后期曾是3K党的聚会场所
was used for Klan meetings in the late 1800s.
- 有谁知道这是不是真的？ - 长官，华盛顿公报打电话来
- Anyone know if this is true？ - I've got the Washington Gazette.
他们想报导 “总统是否漠视少数民族？”
They want a quote on, "Is the president being insensitive to minority issues？"
- 真假已经无所谓了 - 弄张备选地点的清单来…你那儿怎样？
- Doesn't matter. - Get a list of approved alternates.
嗯，我知道是仓促了点
- What do you have？ - Yeah, I know it's short notice.
但我们之前订的饭店，水管爆了
The pipe burst in the hotel that we previously booked.
- 那儿现在水漫金山 - 我要安排个200人规模的退休餐会
- I… There is water everywhere. - A retirement party for 200 people.
- 在冈斯顿庄园 - 蒙蒂塞洛也被定了
- Gunston Hall. - Monticello is booked.
冈斯顿庄园和都铎广场也是一样
So is Gunston Hall and Tudor Place.
登比酒店尚有空缺，还有弗农山庄
The Denby Hotel is available, and so is Mount Vernon.
- 你真是我的大救星啊 - 登比酒店不错
- Oh, wow. You are a lifesaver. - The Denby is great.
不用考虑了，登比酒店刚刚被人订了 只剩弗农山庄了
Strike that. The Denby was booked. Mount Vernon's all we got.
快订，别又让别人订了
Book it before someone else does.
今天能来这儿是本人的莫大荣幸
And let me say what an honor it is to be here
请允许我向总统先生说声，生日快乐
and add my happy birthday to you, Mr. President.
弗吉尼亚  弗农山庄
- 晚上好，先生 - 晚上好
- Good evening, sir. - Good evening.
你知道这儿是管制区域吗？
Are you aware that you are in a restricted area？
知道，但是这儿有鱼啊，年轻人
Yeah, but this is where the fish are, son.
可能吧，但你得把船往上游开
That may be, but I'm gonna need to have you move upriver.
你知道吗，根据马里兰州宪法第25章第1条
Are you aware that according to article one, section 25
我有在公用水域钓鱼的权利
of the Maryland constitution, I'm allowed to fish in public water？
你是否知道，我可以无条件拘留你48小时？
Are you aware I have the right to detain you for the next 48 hours without cause？
我会尽快走人回家的
I am going to go back where I came from just as fast as possible.
等到哪天我受邀参加酒会 说不定也会穿这一身衣服
Maybe one day I'll wear this thing to a party I was actually invited to.
晚8点例检，11区请回话
Twenty hundred time check. Station 11.
- 没有情况，周围安全 - 你好
- All clear. Perimeter secure. - Hey.
你有没有看到附近有个可爱的褐发女子？
You didn't happen to see a cute brunette wandering around？
- 我刚去拿了杯饮料，回来她就不见了 - 没有，先生
- Went to get a drink, she disappeared. - No, sir.
今晚我要放空枪了
I've got no game tonight.
晚上好，阁下…你好
Good evening, Your Excellency. Hello.
首相大人，很高兴您又来美国了
Prime Minister, it's a delight to have you back in the States.
宣传这个观点，竞选赞助限额 并不是强制执行的，因为总统…
Spread the word, contribution limits not enforced on the president's birth…
- 生日快乐，总统先生 - 谢谢
- Happy birthday. - Thank you.
- 我是本・盖茨，记得圣殿财宝么？ - 噢，是你啊，本・盖茨
- Ben Gates. The Templar treasure？ - Oh, right, Ben Gates. Yeah.
- 我们就不占您的时间了 - 非常感谢
- We won't keep you. - Thanks so much. Always a pleasure.
今晚能被邀来参加酒会，我兴奋得要命
I can't tell you what a thrill it is for me to be invited here tonight, sir.
对，现在的你一定让情报机关忙到不行
Yeah, you must have the Secret Service hopping about now.
您说什么？
Sir？
因为你有了新的身世嘛
Considering your discovered lineage.
- 噢，对，那个…… - 继续说吧
- Oh, yeah. Oh, that… - Carry on.
对不起，先生，但是我知道你很崇拜华盛顿
I beg your pardon, sir, but I know what a huge admirer you are
我觉得您该想看看这个
of George Washington. I thought you might want to take a look at this.
看一下
Have a look at that.
这是华盛顿亲手绘制的弗农山庄地图
This is a map of Mount Vernon drawn by George Washington himself.
总统先生，您说的太对了
Mr. President, that is exactly what it is.
- 耶鲁大学，建筑历史系 - 我不知道您是学这个的
- Architectural history major, Yale. - I did not know that.
这是我叔祖父的
It belonged to my great uncle.
原属于叫夏洛特的奴隶的孙女
Got it from the granddaughter of a slave, Charlotte.
- 生日快乐，总统先生 - 非常感谢
- Happy birthday. - Always a pleasure. Thank you so much.
夏洛特曾在弗农山庄工作生活过
Charlotte, who lived here and worked here at Mount Vernon.
- 是啊 - 我们现正站在这个地方
- Yeah. - And we're standing right here, sir.
这条线代表了一条地下通道 一条从未曾被人发现的逃生通道
This line is an underground tunnel, an escape route that was never found.
不知道…不知道现在还在不在
I wonder… I wonder if it's still there.
那么…
Well…
- 要知道答案只有一种方法 - 不如我们去看看
- Only one way to find out, sir. - Maybe we should take a look.
我们可以吗？
Are we allowed to do that？
我知道您当然可以，您是总统
I mean, I know you're allowed to do that. You're the president.
我能跟您一起去吗？
Can I come with you？
- 你们真是无所不在啊 - 是，先生
- You guys are just everywhere. - Yes, sir.
- 把手电给我的朋友 - 谢谢
- Give my friend your flashlight. - Thank you.
根据地图，应该是…
According to this map, it should be…
是一…二，在这儿
It's one… two. In here.
对，应该是这儿
Yeah, should be in here.
- 我可以进去吗？ - 当然
- May I？ - Absolutely.
好
All right.
克雷格，对你的工作我表示感激
You know, Craig, I appreciate you doing your job,
但是这儿没有我的敌人
but I have no enemies down here.
在这个地下室，这个小房间里
In the cellar. In this tiny little room.
那我就在这儿等吧
I'll just wait here, then.
这边
Over here.
- 那是乔治・华盛顿的标记 - 有点不一样
- That's the mark of George Washington. - Only it's slightly different.
- 怎么不一样？ - 斧头的角度不一样
- How？ - These axes, the angle's off.
根据地图上画的，应该是个完美的V字
For it to correspond with the ones on the map, it should form a perfect V.
好，还有什么
OK, what else？
箭头…
The arrowhead…
偏到一边了
…is sideways.
我们很好，别担心
We're all right. Don't worry.
看看
Look at that.
来吧
Come on.
总统先生？
Mr. President？
9区有情况！
We have a breach in zone nine！ There's…
- 通知费尔法克斯郡政府 - 周边通报情况，封锁所有出口
- Inform Fairfax, SecTac Channel One！ - Perimeter detail, lock down all exits！
- 盖茨，你在干什么 - 对不起，总统先生
- Gates, what are you doing？ - I'm sorry, Mr. President.
我必须问您个问题，但我知道 只有我们俩独处时您才会回答
I need to ask you a question, which I know you can't answer unless we're alone.
我们两个进来了！
Two coming in！
我要一把锤子，一把铁撬 还要一台凿石机
I want a sledgehammer, I want a crowbar, I want a jackhammer, now！
汤姆，通知副总统
Tom, alert the vice president.
总统先生，1880年至今
Mr. President, sometime between 1880,
坚定之桌搬入总统办公室后
when the Resolute desk was placed in the Oval Office,
我国有一位总统发现书桌里的秘密夹层
and now, one of our presidents found a secret compartment in the desk.
夹层里有一块写有 印第安人土著文字的木板
Hidden inside was a plank with Native American writing on it.
那是传说中的黄金城――锡沃拉的藏宝图
A treasure map to Cibola, the legendary City of Gold, sir.
你千辛万苦，只是想问我藏宝图？
All this just to ask me about a treasure map？
藏宝图是证明托马斯・盖茨清白的关键
That map is a key to proving Thomas Gates' innocence.
我知道那木板已经不在坚定之桌里了
I know for a fact that the plank is no longer in the Resolute desk.
你已经拜访过我的桌子了？
You've been in my desk too？
我知道那块木板的下落
I believe the whereabouts of that plank is now hidden…
就藏在总统秘卷中
…in the President's Book, sir.
那秘卷只有总统才能看
The book known only to our presidents.
秘卷里有所有的国家机密
It contains all of our nation's secrets.
我从没听过比这更荒唐的事情
That's the most ridiculous thing I've ever heard.
我看过书桌里的徽章 这说明地图的确存在
I saw the seal in the desk, sir. I know the map exists.
你不打算告诉我怎么出去…
You're not going to tell me how to get out of here
- 除非你达到目的 - 出去的路就往那边走
- unless you get what you want. - The way out is that direction,
我会带您出去的
and I'll show you.
你不太会谈判，对吧？
You don't negotiate very well, do you？
不懂，先生
No, sir.
总统先生？
Mr. President！
我要的锤子呢？
Where are my sledgehammers？
我不明白，盖茨
I don't get you, Gates.
你这么做，甚至为此甘愿去坐牢
You do all this, you're willing to go to prison,
就为了洗刷你祖先的名声
just to clear your ancestor's name.
走下阶梯就能出去
The way out is just down those stairs.
没有先人，就没有现在的我
Everything I am is because of my ancestors, sir.
托马斯・盖茨对他的祖国献出满腔热血
Thomas Gates gave his last full measure of devotion
以阻止金环骑士会的阴谋
to his country to stop the KGC.
当一个人为国捐躯时 我相信他该受到赞扬
When someone dies for their country, I believe they should be honored.
“献出满腔热血？”
"Last full measure of devotion"？
林肯是我最喜欢的总统 我没有冒犯您的意思
Lincoln is my favorite president, sir. No offense.
没关系，他也是我心中的英雄
None taken. He's my favorite too.
我知道有这本书，问题是…
Sir, I know the book exists, and my question is,
能否同意让我一观？
"Will you agree to let me see it？"
如果那种东西真的存在
Even if something like that really did exist,
凭什么认为我会给你看？
why do you think I would actually just give it to you？
因为这可能会指引我们
Because it will probably lead us
发现史上最大的印第安宝藏
to the discovery of the greatest Native American treasure of all time.
一块巨大的文化空白
A huge piece of culture lost.
你可以将那段历史交还给它的后代们
You can give that history back to its descendants.
而且因为您是美国总统，先生
And because you're the president of the United States, sir.
无论是您内在的人格，捍卫宪法的誓言
Whether by innate character, or the oath you took to defend the Constitution,
还是肩头的历史重任，您都会这么做的
or the weight of history that falls upon you.
我相信您是位可敬的人，先生
I believe you to be an honorable man, sir.
人民已经不相信这些东西了
People don't believe that stuff anymore.
他们愿意相信
They want to believe it.
最近的公路在那边，恕我无法与您同路了
Nearest highway is that direction. You'll understand if we part ways here.
- 盖茨 - 先生
- Gates. - Sir？
我下面要讲的话，你就当从没听过
The following conversation never happened.
那本书的确存在
The book exists.
- 在哪里？ - 你会把书放在哪里？
- Where is it？ - Where else do you keep a book？
就在国会图书馆
In the Library of Congress.
X，Y，2，3，4，7，8，6
X, Y, two, three, four, seven, eight, six.
谢谢你，先生
Thank you, sir.
还得记住3，7，9，4
You'll also need to know three, seven, nine, four.
知道了
Got it.
- 盖茨 - 先生
- And, Gates… - Sir？
有两百人知道你绑架了我 我无法告诉他们原因
Two hundred people know you held me against my will. I can't tell them why.
除非你找到你需要的东西
Unless you find what you're looking for,
你会被控绑架总统的罪名
you'll be charged with kidnapping the president.
- 你知道那意味着什么 - 是的，非常清楚
- You know what that means. - Yes, sir. Very much so, sir.
- 我要你帮我做件事 - 这是我的荣幸
- I want you to do something for me. - It would be a privilege, sir.
第47页，好好看看
Page 47. Just have a look at that.
莱利，国会图书馆，20分钟后见
Riley, meet me at the Library of Congress in 20 minutes.
好
OK.
我是萨德斯基
Sadusky.
总统他…怎么了？
The president's been what？
是盖茨
Gates.
XY234786
X- Y-two-three-four-seven-eight-six.
XY234786…XY234786…
X- Y-two-three-four-seven-eight-six. X- Y-two-three-four-seven-eight-six.
- 嘿 - 你好
- Hey. - Hey.
谜底就在眼前
We're close.
- 我们从哪儿开始？ - XY是图书分类号
- Where do we start？ - XY is the book classification code.
XY代表特别类，就是非常珍贵的书籍
Stands for special collections, which means very special books.
- 这些书在哪儿？ - 这边走，我们得偷偷溜进去
- Where are they？ - This way. We'll sneak in.
这下好了
This will be good.
到了，XA…XM…
Here we go. XA… XM…
看这儿，你有密码吗？
Look. Do you have a code？
3-7-9-4
Three-seven-nine-four.
总统说书目号是多少？
What did the president say the number was？
是234786
Two-three-four-seven-eight-six.
2-3-6-7…
Two-three-six-seven…
XY233，2378…在这儿
X- Y-two-three-three, two-three-seven-eight… Here.
- 23479… - 78…
- Two-three-four-seven-nine… - Seventy-six, 78…
不在这里
It's not there.
可能有人借出去了
Maybe someone checked it out.
- 既然没书，他为什么叫我们来？ - 也许他是想让我们被捕
- Why send us here if there's no book？ - He probably wanted us to get caught.
看这儿
Here.
- 什么东西 - 六位数字锁
- What is that？ - It's a six-dial combination lock.
书目号就是密码
The location is the combination.
书目号就是密码…
我说的没错吧
Yes. I was right.
干得好，普尔先生
Well done, Mr. Poole.
鹰和卷轴
Eagle and the scroll.
- 51区… - 嘘！
- Area 51！ - Shh！
- 是肯尼迪刺杀案… - 嘘！没时间看这些
- Kennedy assassination. - Shh！ We don't have time.
对，那倒是真的
Yeah, it's true.
这个，等等
Here. Wait.
1865年4月，维多利亚女王给派克发了两封密码信函
"April 1865. Queen Victoria sends Pike two coded missives.
第一封信打开后，里面的信息…
The first is received. Contains information regarding
是有关新大陆宝藏的，黄金之城！
New World treasure. The City of Gold. "
等等，女王想要帮南部邦联的忙？
Wait. The queen wanted to help the Confederacy？
- 分裂的美国更容易对付 - 英国需要南方的棉花
- A divided America'd have been weaker. - Needed cotton from the South.
第二封信据信写有普莱费厄密码
"The second missive was thought to contain a Playfair cipher
建议与拉布莱伊联系 他死前会将线索埋藏起来
suggesting contact with Laboulaye, who'll hide clues before his death. "
那就是布斯日记里写的密码 也是托马斯想烧掉的
The cipher written into the Booth diary page that Thomas tried to burn.
- 就是我们发现的那个 - 没错，1880年…
- The one we have. - Exactly. "1880.
坚定之桌抵达华盛顿 作为女王送给海斯总统的礼物
Resolute desk arrives in Washington, sent by queen to President Hayes. "
看这个
Look at that.
白宫失踪的木板，哇哦
Missing plank from the White House. Wow.
最后一条是柯立芝总统写的
Here's the final entry by President Coolidge.
1924年，我在书桌秘密夹层发现一块板子
"1924. I found a plank in secret desk compartment.
留下照片后，木板被摧毁
Plank photographed and then destroyed.
并委派博格鲁姆去摧毁地标
Borglum commissioned to destroy landmarks
地点在神圣的黑岗山
in sacred Black Hills mountains. "
博格鲁姆？和拉什莫尔山有关系嘛？（拉什莫尔山：即著名的总统山，刻有4名总统的头像）
Borglum. Mount Rushmore？
他在拉什莫尔山上雕刻 是为了抹去地图上的地标
He carved Mount Rushmore to erase the map's landmarks
从而保护黄金之城
in order to protect the City of Gold.
拉什莫尔山竟然是个幌子
Mount Rushmore was a cover-up.
什么声音？
What is it？
那些领我税金的家伙要来捉我了
There's my tax dollars at work, coming to arrest me.
他们是来捉我的，快去开车
Not coming for you, they're for me. Go to the car.
- 不 - 快去，我会同你们会合的
- No！ - Go！ I'll meet up with you.
往这儿走
This way.
盖茨先是绑架了总统，然后又放了他
So Gates abducts the president, lets him go
随后就来到了国会图书馆？
and heads to the Library of Congress？
- 为什么？ - 可能他想借本书看看
- Why？ - Maybe he wants to check out a book.
这边
This way.
所有探员注意…
All agents…
- 爸爸 - 本
- Dad. - Ben.
快点出来，我得把车开走了
Get out of there. I had to move the car.
满大街都是FBI和特勤局的人
FBI, Secret Service all over the place.
别慌，我先把木板的照片发到你手机上
Calm down. I sent a picture of the plank to your cell.
- 你能把照片发过来？ - 对，我能
- You can do that？ - Yes, I can do that.
收到照片了吗？
Did you get it？
- 收到了 - 看
- I got it. - Look.
- 拿去给妈妈翻译 - 为什么让我去？
- Take it to Mom for translation. - Why me？
他说他妈妈可以翻译木板？
He say his mom could translate the plank？
查查她的底细
Find out who she is.
- 我们怎么去找本？ - 不知道
- How are we going to find Ben？ - I don't know.
- 站住！你们是谁？ - 我们是工作人员
- Hold it！ Who are you？ - We work here.
- 身份卡 - 拿去，有人叫我们疏散
- IDs. - Here. We were told to evacuate.
我不知道里面发生了什么事
I don't know what's going on.
- 我的车停在… - 前一秒我还在看书…
- My car's parked… - One second I'm reading…
- 一个特别的区域… - 转眼间就被赶了出来…
- Special section for… … a book, then we're rushed out…
- 走吧 - 谢谢
- Go ahead. - OK. Thank you.
- 遇见人最好拿出身份卡，祝你们好运 - 多谢你的帮助，警官
- Thank you for your help, officer. - Best of luck.
晚安
Have a good night.
到东北区去…
Hey, go to the northeast sectors…
发动引擎
Start the car.
挂好排档
Put it in gear.
怎么回事？
- Uh-oh. - What's the problem？
没问题，快开车
It's clear. Let's go！
我们会坐牢的
We're going to jail.
我要检查一下…
I want to run a check…
进来，抓稳
Get in！ Hang on！
一辆奔驰SUV…
Mercedes SUV…
- 他上来了，快开车！ - 抓稳了！
- He's in！ Go！ - Hang on！
好，我们能行的
OK. We can do this.
升起路障，封住出口！
Close the barricade, lock it down！
封住出口！
Lock it down！
- 快开，快开 - 好
- Drive, drive, drive！ - OK.
不行！
I don't think so！
快！快！快！
Go, go, go, go, go！
快走！快点！
Let's go！ Let's go！
这跟计划中的不一样！
That did not turn out the way it was supposed to！
- 他们怎么这么快就找到我们了？ - 我来告诉你是怎么回事
- How'd they find us so quick？ - I'll tell you how.
- 总统他打了小报告！ - 是萨德斯基，刚才在图书馆见到他了
- The president is a tattletale！ - Sadusky. He was there.
关于那本书，看来他知道不少
He knows more about the book than I thought.
被人绑架，总统先生他感觉如何啊？
How'd the president feel about being kidnapped？
还行吧
He was OK.
- 阿普尔顿博士 - 办公室已经关门了，不好意思
- Dr. Appleton. - This office is closed. I'm sorry.
抱歉这么晚打扰
I do apologize for the lateness of the hour.
我的名字是米奇・威尔金森
My name is Mitch Wilkinson.
我想让你看个东西，很快就好
I've got something I want you to take a look at. Just take a minute.
- 你是宝藏猎人 - 不，女士
- You're a treasure hunter. - No, ma'am.
我只是一个想青史留名的人
I'm just a man trying to make his mark on history.
能帮我吗？
Can you help me？
我不懂那种语言，抱歉，帮不上忙
Um… No, I don't know that language. I'm sorry. I can't help you.
请原谅
Oh, excuse me.
对
Yes.
知道了
Got it.
你的前夫正在路上，他也想要你的翻译
Your ex-husband's on his way up. He wants the translation.
不许告诉他真相，甩开他 否则他的命就难保了
Tell him anything but the truth. Get rid of him. His life depends on it.
艾米丽？
Emily？
我知道你最不想见的人就是我
I know I'm the last person you want to see,
我也觉得很别扭，但我们需要你翻译点东西
and I'm not comfortable either, but we need you to translate something.
- 本让我来的，他需要你帮忙 - 那没问题
- Ben sent me. He needs your help. - Yes, of course.
如果是本，就没问题，是什么东西？
If it's for Ben, of course. What is it？
在手机里，我不知道怎么…
It's in the cell phone. I'm not sure how to…
- 给我 - …把图片调出来
- Give it to me. … bring it out.
我们知道这地方应该在拉什莫尔山附近
We know it leads to Mount Rushmore.
对，“岛…草之海中，石之岛耸”
Yes. "Islands… Islands of stone in a sea of grass. "
那是拉科塔土著用来称呼 南达科他州的黑岗山
That's what the Lakota used to call the Black Hills in South Dakota.
嗯
Right.
“月侵地处，蜂鸟翼舒”
"Find where the moon touches the earth and release the hummingbird. "
只有这些？
That's it？
你有没有想过…？没想到我会说出来
Did it ever occur to you？ I can't believe I'm saying this.
你有没有想过 我做那些事是为了引你注意？
Did it ever occur to you that I did the things I did to impress you？
不，你只是自己想做，而我也会做同样的事
No, you did it because you wanted to, and I would've done the same thing,
只是我们有人得负责养家育儿
except one of us had to grow up and stay home and look after Ben.
当然那绝对不是你
Certainly wasn't going to be you.
你有没有想过，是我做出你做不来的牺牲？
Did it ever occur to you that I made sacrifices for us that you never did？
肯定没有
No, of course not.
你还是走吧
So just go away.
可恶的龙舌兰酒
Lousy tequila.
别再沮丧了，你做得很好
Don't feel bad. You did good.
帕特里克对你的话深信不疑
Patrick believed every word you said.
而且，你儿子他找不到宝藏的
Besides, your son would have never found the treasure anyway.
你不了解本杰明
You don't know Benjamin.
也许我不了解，但是我有这个
Perhaps not. But then again, I have this.
维多利亚女王写给南军将领派克的信？
A letter from Queen Victoria to the Confederate General Albert Pike？
我们的女王似乎更偏爱南部邦联
Seems the dear old queen was partial to the Confederate cause.
这封信在我的家族中已经传承了140年
This has been handed down by my family for 140 years.
里面有最重要的信息，也是最后的线索
Contains a vital piece of information. The final clue, as it were.
若没有你的翻译，这条信息毫无价值
This piece of information is worthless without your translation of the planks.
真是讽刺啊
It's ironic, isn't it？
一切都从烧毁一页纸开始
This all began with the burning of pages, and now it ends
结局却是烧毁这个最终的线索
with the burning of this, the final clue.
让我成为唯一
Making me the only one…
能找到锡沃拉的人
…who can find Cibola.
带上外套
Get your coat.
就她对第二块板子的翻译来看
Her translation on the second half of the planks says
- 我们要找的是一个石之岛 - 本应该已经找到了
- we need to find an island of stone. - Ben would have found it by now.
我不这么认为
I don't think so.
怎么才能到这里…
How do I get to, um, this…
你好，米奇
Hello, Mitch.
妈妈…
Mom…
- 等我一下 - 没门，你太慢啦
- Wait for me. - No way. You're too slow.
我跟你爸说的那些话，我就知道你能明白的
I knew you'd figure out the message I gave your father.
“蜂鸟”这谜语真不错…放了她，米奇（关于蜂鸟之谜的猜测，请看片尾字幕）
The hummingbird was good. Let her go.
枪在我们手上，轮不到你发号施令
We're the ones with the firepower, and you're giving me orders.
我绑架了总统，FBI现在正抓我呢
I kidnapped the president. The FBI is on their way right now to arrest me,
相信他们见到你会很高兴的
and I'm sure they'll love to meet you.
他们会找到我们两个，然后拿出两付手铐
They'll find us both and arrest us both.
顺着那条路可没法走到黄金之城，对吧？
That path doesn't lead to the City of Gold, does it？
这个人身上有你需要的线索，他有封信
This man has information you need. He's got a letter.
维多利亚女王给阿尔伯特・派克将军的信
From Queen Victoria to General Albert Pike.
- 你怎么知道？ - 我从一本书里看到的
- How do you know that？ - I read about it, in a book.
那封信他已经烧掉了
I'm afraid he's burned it.
好吧…你让我做了这么多 为何现在却要半途而废呢？
All right… You've had me do all the work so far, why stop now？
把你知道的告诉我，我去找黄金之城
You tell me what you know, I'll find the City of Gold,
只要能证明托马斯・盖茨的清白，宝藏归你
prove Thomas Gates' innocence, you can have the treasure.
- 什么？ - 我跟你一起去
- What？ - I'm going with you.
但如果别人问起黄金之城是谁发现的
But if anyone's gonna be credited for discovering the City of Gold,
答案只有一个，那就是我
it's going to be me.
但你的同伙都得留在这儿，不许带枪
But your partners stay here, and all the guns.
凭什么觉得我会同意这条件？
What makes you think I'd agree？
因为你需要这笔财宝，这一点我很清楚
Because you need that treasure. Believe me, I know.
好吧，我们按你说的做
All right, Gates. We'll do it your way.
但是相信我…带没带枪，对我都一样
But believe me… I don't need the guns.
- 哪个总统？美国总统？ - 我觉得还是不告诉你为好
- Which president？ The president？ - I thought it best not to tell you.
我还是看不到什么尊鸟的影子
I still don't see anything that looks like a noble bird.
好吧，告诉我们
All right. Let's have it.
信上写了什么？女王的信有什么线索？
What did the letter say？ What's the clue from Queen Victoria's letter？
无云之雨，出入之闾
"The entrance shall only be revealed under a cloudless rain. "
来解解看这个谜语吧
Figure that one out.
我们等下雨的时候再来？
So we come back when it's raining？
无云可能指的就是太阳
"Cloudless. " Could simply mean the sun.
在晴天的时候…下雨
You need a sunny day… and rain.
我们用水造雨
We need water.
水
Water.
阿比盖尔
Abigail.
各位，水会让石头颜色变深，用水浇石头
Everybody, the water makes the rocks darker. Use the water.
艾米丽？要水么？
Em？ Water？
- 我手上的是什么？你没长眼睛啊？ - 好，好
- What's this in my hand？ Are you blind？ - Good, good, good.
太可笑了，要把水洒遍这座山？
This is ridiculous. Are we going to water the whole thing？
就是这个
That's it.
这是这个！我找到了，这边，这边！
Oh！ That's it. I found it. Over here！ Found it！ Over here！
看看
Look at this！
一只鹰
It's an eagle.
- 看啊，是一只鹰 - 还真有哎
- Look at that. It's an eagle. - There it is.
- “尊鸟有缘…” - “路在眼前”
- "The noble bird… " - "Will give you passage. "
- 现在怎么办？ - 我们应该手拉手…
- Uh-huh. Now what？ - We need to join hands,
摆出优雅高贵的姿态，走过这只鸟
and in a noble manner, pass over the bird.
- 也许它指示了方向… - 也许这鸟就会…
- It indicates direction… - Somehow that bird…
从石头上飞起，然后哑哑鸣叫…
…will rise from the rock and kind of caw…
你们要么继续胡猜瞎蒙 要么听我道出下一个线索
You can stand around guessing for a while, or I can give you the next clue.
“勇士心上，举手示降”
"Surrender your hand to the heart of the warrior. "
鹰就是勇士的标志
And the eagle is a symbol of the warrior.
本，别，等等，先别伸手
Ben, no. Wait, wait！ No.
这可能是个可怕的陷阱，快告诉他！
That's probably a horrible trap. Tell him！
这是个可怕的陷阱
It's a horrible trap.
都已经到门口了，还不试试，太可惜了
It would be a pity to come this far and not even try, now, wouldn't it？
我来吧，本
I'll do it, Ben.
没关系
It's OK.
举手示降…
Surrender your hand.
- 不好意思，我…我实在忍不住 - 你…
- I am sorry. I… I couldn't resist. - You！
摸起来好像是个门拴
Lt, uh… feels like a latch.
看看
Look at this.
好，走吧
All right, good. Let's go.
本，过来看看这个
Ben, look at this.
太漂亮了！
Oh, that's beautiful！
- 帕特里克！ - 本，那是什么？
- Patrick. Patrick！ - Ben, what is that？
像是个砝码，为保持平衡，不让门关上
Appears to be a counterweight to hold the door open.
什么声音？
What is that sound？
太迷人了
Fascinating.
本！
Ben！
对不起
Sorry.
- 还好吧？ - 不好
- You OK？ - No.
起来
Get up.
锁住了
It's locked.
- 帕特里克，瞧你都干了什么？ - 门闩自己合上了，不是我干的
- Patrick, what have you done？ - Some kind of a bolt. I didn't do it.
只有一种出去的方法了
Only one way out of here now.
往前走
Forward.
从没看到过这么多文物
Never seen so many relics.
保存如此完好
So beautifully preserved.
各位，看来我们得把这些石头搬走
Looks like we're going to be moving some rocks.
- 那后面有个通道 - 都来看看这个
- There's a tunnel back in through here. - Guys, look at this.
小金人
It's a little golden man.
看，它的身体特别小，看啊，他好像…
Look. It's got a tiny little torso. Look at that. It looks like…
- 本！ - 本！
- Ben！ - Ben！
后退，后退，你们都到另外一边去！
Move back！ Move back！ All of you！ Other side！
后退！
Back up！ Back up！
莱利，往前，往前！
Riley, move forward！ Move forward！
不，退后，退后！
No, back up, back up.
- 你要我干嘛？ - 停，停下！
- What you want me to do？ - Stop！ Stop！
我们得控制重心，这块板才不会翻
We have to balance our weight to even this thing out.
- 我们会找到他们的 - 我们怎么办？
- We'll find 'em. - What are we gonna do？
- 我有个主意，我告诉你该怎么办 - 不，我有个主意
Figure something out. Tell you what we're going to do.
不，让我来说
- No, I'll tell you. - No. I'll tell you！
不，让我来说！那里有个通道
No, I'll tell you！ There's that passageway.
你去把那些石头搬开，那肯定通向什么地方
You go, pull those stones out, because that leads somewhere.
真是一个好主意
That is a good idea.
下面没东西，只有一个黑乎乎的大洞
There's nothing. Just a big old black hole.
本，看那儿！有个梯子
Ben, look！ There's a ladder.
- 我的意思是，至少以前是个梯子 - 手电扔给我
- I mean, what's left of a ladder. - Toss me the light.
莱利，慢慢移动到那个角上，不，等下…
Riley. Move slowly to that corner. No！ Wait. Just…
- 等我往这个角上移的时候你再移 - 好
- As I move to this corner. - OK.
一次一步，很好
One step at a time. Good.
如果能让这一角升高点，我应该能够到
If we can raise this corner, I think I'll reach it.
- 停！红灯！ - 你在帮倒忙！
- Stop！ Red light！ - You're not helping！
我像你一样，也可以够得到
I can get up there just as easy as you.
先停下
Just stop.
- 你们！ - 这里是三对一
- Guys！ - It's three against one here.
我不愿最后走，既然如此 那不妨让我最先走
I ain't going last, and if I'm not going last, I might as well go first.
听着
Look！
怎么样？
What's it gonna be？
我们按你说的做
We'll do this your way.
其他人，听我数三声，然后聚拢
The rest of us, on my count of three, all move together.
一次一步
One step at a time.
一，二，三
One, two, three.
- 准备好了？ - 走
- You ready？ - Go.
米奇，你看到什么了？
Mitch, what do you see？
是出去的路吗？
Is there a way out？
上面是什么，米奇？
What's up there, Mitch？
艾米丽？
Em？
- 你还好吗？ - 向我保证，他会没事的
- Are you all right？ - Just promise me he's gonna be OK.
好
All right.
我们走
Let's go.
米奇！快回答！
Mitch！ Come on！
- 我刚才算过了… - 我知道
- I've been doing the math here, and… - I know.
我们得留一个人在这儿
We're gonna have to leave one person behind.
答应我，你们会回来找我
Promise you'll come back for me.
我也会算啊
I can do the math too.
- 那下一个该你上了 - 我最后走
- That makes you next. - I'll go last.
“不，我们会想个其它办法的” “我们需要你，求你了，莱利”
"No, we'll figure something else out. " "We need you there. Please, Riley. "
我开玩笑，你们走吧
I'm just kidding. Go.
好…
OK…
- 一…二…三！ - 走！
- One… two… three！ - Go！
- 你干了什么？ - 什么也没干
- What are you doing？ - Nothing.
我抓不到
I can't get it.
走！现在就走！快！
Just go！ Go now！ Go！
- 好，准备好了？ - 走！
- All right, ready？ - Now！
莱利！ 抓紧了！
Riley！ Hang on！
嘿，米奇，那雕像 本，我们发现了个金雕像
OK. Mitch, the idol. OK, Ben. We found a gold idol here！
我们可以用雕像来平衡你的重量
We can roll it over to offset your weight！
那就快点！
Then roll it！
来了！
Here it comes！
快，本！
Come on, Ben！
来，抓住我的手
Here！ Give me your hand！
本！
Ben！
谢谢，莱利
Thanks, Riley.
在我见义勇为的时候为啥没有女孩旁观呢？
Why couldn't a girl see me do that？
- 你还好吗？ - 没事了，你安全了
- You all right？ - You're OK. You're OK. You're OK.
那么…往前走吧
So… forward.
这是什么？
What is this？
把你的灯放在这里
Put your light over there.
你在干什么？
What are you doing？
我什么也看不到！是不是到了？
I can't see anything！ Is this it？
是油！
It's oil！
是死路！没有出路！
It's a dead end！ There's no way out！
我们得折回去！
We have to turn back！
好
OK.
不不，帕特里克，这太疯狂了
No. No, Patrick, this is crazy.
好了
OK.
成功了
I got it！
抓住你了！抓住你了！
I got you！ I got you！
不能再往前了
There's no forward！
不是往前，是往下！
It's not forward, it's down！
这些水一定从某处排出去 不然就会淹满这里
All this water has to go out somewhere. Otherwise, it'd be filled up.
来帮我推这个转盘！
Help me turn this wheel！
水是往下流的
The water's going down.
那些是…艾米丽
It is… Em.
艾米丽，艾米丽
Em. Em.
本！
Ben！ Hey！
爸爸！我们找到了！
Dad！ We found it！
- 托马斯说得没错！ - 不，是你说得没错
- Thomas was right！ - No, you were right！
对不起，我玷污了你先祖的美名
Sorry I smeared your great-great granddaddy's good name.
但这可能是唯一能让你上钩的方法
Seemed like the only way to get you in on the hunt.
这机会能让威尔金森家族留名青史
But this was a chance for the Wilkinson family to make its mark on history,
发现黄金之城，并被后世铭记
to find the City of Gold, to be remembered.
刚才发生什么了？你爸爸担心死了
What happened to you？ Your father was worried sick about you.
她差点疯掉
She was frantic. She was frantic.
爸爸，来的路上，你有没有看到…
Dad, coming through, did you happen to see？
住手，你有看到可以出去的岔路吗？
Stop it. Coming through, did you see any branches that could lead out？
没，都堵住了，连门口都回不去
No, it's all blocked. You can't even get back to the big, round stone door.
你母亲去干什么
Where's your mother going？
亲爱的，亲爱的，看看这个
Sweetheart. Sweetheart. Have a look at this.
- 什么？ - 看啊
- What？ - Look.
有了这个，就能解读奥尔麦克的文字
This is gonna unlock the Olmec language.
前哥伦布时期的美洲历史将变得豁然开朗
It's gonna give us incredible insight into pre-Columbian history.
艾米丽
Em？
- 开心吗？ - 嗯，开心
- You happy？ - Oh, yeah.
- 本，来看这个，来啊！ - 就是这个
- Ben！ Look at this！ Look！ - Oh, yeah.
这是他们割喉取心（祭神）的地方
That's where they slit the throat, cut the heart out.
- 什么声音？ - 听
- What was that？ - Listen.
我要找个出口，所有的门都堵上了
I tried to find a way out. All those portals are blocked off！
这些水总要从某个地方出去，我们会找到的
I'm telling you, all this water goes out somewhere. We'll find it.
本，水往那儿流
Ben, there's a current！
跟着找！这里肯定有个中央排水口
Follow it！ There's got to be a central drain！
就在我们脚下，就这儿！
It's under us. Right here！
快！
Come on！
我们走！进去！
Let's go！ Get in there！
水位上升太快了！
The water's rising too fast！
只要打开那道门，就不会被水淹死！
Let's get that door open so we don't all drown！
本，水顺着斜坡下去了！是一条排水管道
Ben, it slopes down！ It's a drainage tunnel.
把门打开后，水会充满通道的
It fills with water when you open the door！
我们得找点东西顶在下面，让门开着
We need to find something to stick under it to keep it open！
不，如果一直开着，这通道就会被淹
No, if it's open, this tunnel will stay flooded.
我们必须先过去，然后把门关了
We've got to get to the other side and close the door.
帕特里克，艾米丽，走！
Patrick, Emily, go！
- 不！ - 不！
- No. - No！
不！
No！
米奇，我们得到门的另一边去！
Mitch, we got to be on the other side of that door！
除非我同意，否则谁都不准走
Nobody leaves unless I say so.
门不会自己一直开着
That door is not gonna stay open by itself.
接下去该怎么做，你我都明白
We both know what has to happen here.
为了让门开着，我们中的一个得留在后面
One of us keeps the door open and stays behind.
我投米奇一票
I vote Mitch.
这不是民主表决
This isn't a democracy.
停手！我留下！我留下好了！看着！
Stop！ I'll stay！ I'm staying. Look. Look！
看见没？我就在这儿，我留下来！
See？ I'm right here！ I'm staying！
接下去怎么走，大家听好了
I'll tell everybody how this is going to go.
你我负责把这门打开，要是谁想走在我前面
You and me are going to open that door. Anybody tries to leave before me,
我就把门放下，然后从头开始
I drop the door, we start this all over again！
有谁耍花招，就要他好看！
Try any funny business, I guarantee you people are going to get hurt！
我不会的！我向你保证，先放了她吧
I won't！ You have my word. Just let her go.
本，你不走我们也不走
Ben, no, we're not leaving without you.
阿比盖尔
Abigail.
你带我父母先走，带我父母先走
You make my parents leave. You make my parents leave.
- 不！ - 走！
- No！ - Let's go！
走吧，求求你们了！ 帕特里克，艾米丽，他是在救我们的命
Let's go, please！ Patrick, Emily, he's trying to save our lives.
快，快点
Please, come on.
推啊，本
Push, Ben！
水流太强了！
The current's too strong！
- 我准备好了！ - 靠你一个了！
- I'm ready！ - It's all yours！
妈妈！
Mom！
坚持！
Hang on！
屏住呼吸！
Hold your breath！
我们得把本弄出来
We got to get Ben out of there！
如果我卡住门，门就关不上
If I'm stuck in the door, it stays open,
两个房间都会被淹，我们全部淹死
both rooms fill up, and we all drown！
- 打开门！我来换你！ - 水流太强了！
- Open the door！ I'll get you out！ - The current's too strong！
如果我打开门，你们全都会被冲走的
I open the door, you'll be washed down！
我会让你出去的！
I'll get you out！
我发现了黄金之城！是我发现的！
I found the City of Gold！ I found it！
得让外人知道这一切！
And no one will ever know？
我们可以想办法！大家都能出去的！
We can figure this out！ We can all get out！
这不是一个谜语，本，谜语说完了！
It's not a puzzle！ No more puzzles, Ben！
要么大家一起死，要么只死我一个！
We're all going to die, or it could just be me！
- 告诉大家，是我发现的！ - 别放弃！
- Tell them I found it！ - Don't quit！
米奇！
Mitch！
谢谢！
Thank you.
- 我们还没正式介绍过，我是莱利 - 噢，你好
- We haven't officially met. I'm Riley. - Oh, hi.
长官！找你的
Sir！ It's for you.
我是萨德斯基
Sadusky.
- 我找到证据了 - 本！
- I have my proof. - Ben！
我们刚还在谈论你呢，准备自首了吗？
We were just talking about you. Ready to turn yourself in？
还没准备好，我们发现了黄金之城
Not quite. We found the City of Gold.
这跟我无关，你已经犯下了重罪
Doesn't matter. You still committed a federal crime.
停下，别敲了！
Stop. Stop it.
- 总统先生？ - 克雷格，给我一分钟
- Mr. President？ - Craig, give us a minute.
先生，据您所说，此人绑架过你
Sir, for your information, this is the man who kidnapped you.
可我记得，我们俩只是在密道里探险
As I recall, we were exploring a hidden tunnel,
身后的门突然关死了，是他把我救了出来
and a door closed accidentally, and this man saved my life.
是，先生
Yes, sir.
- 盖茨 - 先生
- Gates. - Sir.
我要把这些话记下来 历经几个世纪的探险后，就在今天
For the record, after centuries of exploration, on this day,
你给你的家族和国家带来了荣耀
you have brought honor to your country and your family.
你为国家做了杰出的贡献，我感谢你
You've done this country a great service. I thank you.
- 谢谢 - 克雷格…
- Thank you. - Craig.
我觉得你可能想看看明天的报纸头版
I thought you might want to take a look at tomorrow's headlines.
明天的？
Tomorrow？
托马斯・盖茨被追认为内战英雄
谢谢你，先生
Thank you, sir.
你们所有的人，包括艾米丽和帕特里克・盖茨
All of you, along with Emily and Patrick Gates
由于参与了这项发现，都会受到表彰
will get credit for this discovery.
还有米奇・威尔金森，先生
And Mitch Wilkinson, sir.
- 是吗？ - 是的，先生
- Is that right？ - It's true, sir.
本，我很好奇我请你帮的那个忙
Ben, I am curious about that favor I asked you.
47页有什么？
Any report regarding what's on page 47？
我想我帮得上忙
I believe I can help with that, sir.
- 那很好 - 人生无常，总统先生
- So it's good. - Life-altering, sir.
47页上有什么？你们在说那本书？
What's on page 47？ Are you talking about the Book？
什么书？
What book？
那东西要小心伺候…你用的是蒸馏水吗？
Be very careful with that. Is that distilled water you're using？
- 是的，女士 - 所有这些东西都登记编目了吗？
- Yes. - Have you catalogued all of this？
- 没有，女士 - 你没有？
- No, ma'am. - You haven't？
抱歉？你在编这个的目录吗？
Excuse me？ Excuse me, sir？ Are you cataloguing this？
我们买沙发时，你真该在场
You should've been there when we picked out our first couch.
对不起
Excuse me.
你就是那个…那个宝藏猎人，对吗？
Hey, you're that guy… The treasure hunter guy, right？
我不是，事实上你要找的人在那边
No, actually, the guy you're thinking of is somewhere over there.
不，你就是那作者，莱利・普尔 我是从你的书上认出你的
No. You're him. Riley Poole. I recognize you from your book.
可以为我签名吗？
Will you sign it？
好啊
OK.
谢谢
Thank you.
那么，关于茶几…
So, um, the tea tables…
哦，下周我会请人搬到你那里去的
Yes, I'm going to have the movers bring them to you next week.
我刚想说，你可以留着茶几
I was going to say you can keep them.
而且你还可以…
And maybe you could…
搬回来跟我住
…come and move back in with me.
- 不，你刚才用了“那么”这个词 - 那么？
- No. You used the word "so. " - So？
那么，你用“那么”的时候说明你很生气
So, when you say "so," it means you're angry.
有时候是，但有时候不是
Sometimes. And then sometimes it doesn't.
有点像个谜语
It's sort of like a puzzle.
你对谜语这么在行，相信你一定解得开
And you're so good at puzzles. I'm sure you'll figure it out.
那么…
So…
莱利・普尔先生敬启
华盛顿  白宫  总统办公室
免税
我爱死这辆车了
I love this car.
== 谢谢观赏 ==
片尾加注：关于谜语“蜂鸟”的推测： 古代美洲文明种族阿兹特克人传说中的主神（战神兼太阳神）名叫胡特兹罗普特利
在当地语言中，这名字由两个词相合而成：“蜂鸟”和“左边” 而阿兹特克人认为向左就是南方，因此左边也可解释为南面
除事态紧急（战神）之外，本的母亲想通过 密码告诉本会合的地点，就在总统山的南坡 片中印证了这一点（总统头像面向东南）
密文前一句“月侵地处”是为了帮本确认： 神话中战神的母亲是大地女神，因一个羽球 而得孕，战神的姐姐认为此胎不祥，欲杀母
在母亲倒地时，战神出世，为了给母亲报仇 他杀了姐姐及从人，并将姐姐的头抛向天空 变成了月亮，所以他姐姐又称“月亮女神”
月亮神戮杀大地神，战神“蜂鸟南飞”出生 这就是“月侵地处，蜂鸟翼舒”一句的由来 而谜底应该是――危险，向南